He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons, and saints.
in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular materialism to see and to know reality
as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage with it well? How do we permeate
everyday life with spiritual presence? Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen
Daymak and Father Stephen De Young host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation.
The union of the scene and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Greetings, Dragon Slayers, Giant Killers.
You are in the unfortunate position
of listening to the 136th episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
I'm Father-In-Dusty even Dame,
extilin' a Mayas Pennsylvania for now.
And with me is Father-Steven Dion, not the swamp thing,
but certainly a swamp thing.
The grief calls to you.
coming to you live from Lafayette.
Louisiana and we are live and we're going to start taking your calls in the second half of the show
tonight we're talking about a huge topic salvation all Christians use this term
wait are are we live? I think so or is this movie do we deserve to be?
most people won't even know the difference because and is that the question?
And if so, who answers?
Who answers?
Thank you.
You completely got me stuck to that.
Who?
As is my want.
Yes.
Actually, I literally ran across a tweet today saying that someone started saying as is my want because they heard you and occasionally me saying that.
So, you say you literally ran across it like someone left their phone on the ground?
That's correct.
Yes, so good in my car.
Yeah.
Um...
Yeah, yeah, Salvation. We're talking about salvation. All Christians use this term.
Do we all mean the same thing by it? No, we clearly do not. Is it possible to have a full
orb-dunderstanding of salvation by closely looking at the Scriptures? Yes. Obviously,
rhetorical questions. So that was easy. Good night.
Actually, I'm going to leave Father Stephen to ramble for the next three hours alone, which
from what I have read is
a number of you out there in podcast land have been hoping for for literally years now.
So you just took our lead in like really literally and they're going full-time sabbatical.
Or or Father Stephen you can start by telling me whether theos theoses they say theosis.
Theos theos. Just say theosis. I know it sounds like it's some kind of like halotosis like osmosis.
It's like asthma.
I know it's theoses or Moses who
Supposes his tozes or roses whether
theoses is it really just an orthodox
add-on to this idea of salvation or
or what is it in the Bible Father
Stephen what this by options where
it's an add-on or what I choose what
Yes, so we're going to be talking about what salvation is, how you get it, not so much
about whether you can lose it, that's a whole other topic.
Well somebody calls in to ask that question.
You get free will, free will, baptismal line.
Yes, yes.
and or a Calvinist, a pugnacious Calvinist.
But yeah, one is salvation and how do we get it?
And so salvation, getting saved, are you saved?
You've been saved.
It's one of those terms that everybody from a Christian background
uses all the time.
Yeah.
But I think often if pressed,
Right, we'll have a hard time.
defining exactly what it means. Or you'll get into the weeds of what we call
satireology. So you know probably I think the most common way people understand
that getting saved is they think it means that you're gonna go to heaven and
So that how would you die?
Yeah, you...
had a conversion experience you got saved.
And so that you're going to go to heaven instead of hell.
I haven't ever lasting is your reward.
Plead into by the whole Walmart parking lot of Angeles,
evangelism tactic of if you died tonight, do you know where you?
I know I had someone do that to me one time.
And I was quite quite a bit younger than I am now.
And I said, um, I'm a Christian, dude.
and the guys start to press
me though, like no, no, do you know? I was like, I mean, look, I've done the thing. I'm
a Christian. I go to church. He couldn't. He just had a script, I guess. I don't know. It was weird.
Yeah. You should have told him you'd been you've been wicked and so you were going to Indiana when you die.
But yeah, is Indiana the afterlife for Ohio? Is that what it is?
If you're bad. It's like the droos believe if you if you're really good at life, you get re-incarnated
in.
China. Right. I mean, there's, you know, traditional
Finnish pangatism, hell is basically an island off of Finland.
Yes. So in this case, Ohioans are the opposite of the
droves and Indiana is the opposite of China.
I'm seeing it. Yeah. I think it's, I don't see how anyone
could doubt those connections. Um,
But that definition
going to have a save hell when you die is literally never what the word saved means in the Bible.
Yeah. Yeah. That all ever, not once. Right. Um, and in fact, that term is used with subtly
different shades of meaning in different parts of the Bible and in different contexts.
And so...
uh we're gonna we're gonna do what we love to do on this show. Start at the very beginning of the
book of Genesis. It's a very good place to start. We're gonna we're gonna take you on a survey
of uh what the word what salvation means in some of these different contexts and how one
gets receives.
achieves accomplishes it.
Right?
So that's our trajectory for this episode.
So that we can read and understand that term in Scripture a little more knowingly.
So we start with Adam,
Our first person.
He was not a shooter.
But we start with Adam and we're actually starting with Adam before the expulsion from paradise.
Pre-Lepsyrian man as it were. Yes, Adam in Eden. This is where we're starting.
And that may seem counterintuitive based on the way salving.
is talked about in a lot of circles.
Yeah, usually it's this idea that salvation
is a thing that happens because things went wrong.
Right. Adam messes things up,
and so now people need to be saved.
Yeah.
Save from what Adam did,
the consequences of what Adam did,
God being mad at Adam for what he did
and taking it out on the rest of us.
Right, however you're saying that.
and that but
question what is salvation for Adam in the Christian tradition? And I'm saying it that way
deliberately because I know but what I want to be fair, right? But also, right, a version
of this understated dig is not foreign to even Protestantism, like classical.
actual Protestantism. This way of thinking may be very foreign to a lot of evangelical folks.
Where is it for them? The idea that the question, what is salvation for Adam? Is a coherent question?
Right. There was salvation for Adam. Adam was on a path to salvation.
and need. And the great evidence of that, of course, is that
Contra certain play-dobrained individuals.
Adam and all of creation for that matter is created in motion.
Adam was not created in a kind of static, unchanging perfection.
Yeah, right. If he had been he couldn't have sent. Right.
There had to be mutability for him to sin, like definitionally.
So Adam is created, all of creation, everything that is created is created.
In motion, toward a tellos, toward a perfection of that thing,
a perfection of each created nature.
So Adam was created toward a tellos, toward an end,
toward a goal, toward a purpose, in motion, toward it.
But that motion in change also allows for motion away from.
Yeah, and he couldn't have fallen if Adam was created as sort of this crystallized perfection.
Right.
So, what did this path or this road toward maturity or perfection or completion mean for Adam?
Well, if you look at
classical Protestant sources that have this understanding. What they will talk about is,
they will say, well, Adam is created and he's given one command. And you may even have heard
this idea even in Orthodox circles, even in Roman Catholic circles, right? Adam has given
one command. And in the
classical Protestant view, Adam was undergoing a sort of probationary period.
And if he had kept that one commandment to not eat from the tree of the knowledge of good and evil,
And he had not done that for some period, for some period of time.
He would have passed probation and essentially been safe.
He would have then been transformed sort of automatically into his perfected state in which
often, depending on who you're reading, he would have been kind of crystallized.
So this is less an image of a path or a road he was on as God was
testing him. If he had succeeded, he would have been rewarded. He failed so he was punished.
Right. That's that sort of paradigm. But if we read closely in Genesis,
it is not in fact the case that he only received one command.
Yeah. He received three commandments.
There are three imperatives.
two of them positive and then the one negative.
And so the one negative commandment we've already talked about,
three of knowledge of good and evil of that tree he was not to eat.
But remember, as we've talked about on the show before,
he received two others to number one, fill the earth,
fill it with life and number two subdue it. Put it into order.
So he had two positive commands, one negative command.
Don't do this. Do do these two things.
And this is why we have the idea of him being on a road or a path or on a way,
toward perfection because filling the earth is something that would have taken place over time,
a series of choices.
Well, in perfection.
You know, sometimes people think of, you know, to be perfect is to be one rather than zero.
You know, like those are the only two options.
You know, like they say, well, I'm not perfect, meaning I've done bad things.
And so therefore, perfection must mean I've done no bad things.
But also there's a sense of perfection as in maturity, something getting riper, better, more fully what it's supposed to be.
That doesn't mean that's not mean there's flaws in it.
Just that it's not there yet like a baby is not perfect
Because a baby is is not full grown
right
And is in a process that will lead to that right
Yeah, and so
Commandments this is it gonna be important
We tend to attach the idea of commandments directly to the idea of sin
You
Commandments are just telling you not to do certain things, right?
Then our bad things.
But that's not commandments are just imperatives.
You can have a negative or a positive imperative.
Right.
If I tell you, go out there, find something good to eat and enjoy yourself.
That's an imperative.
That's a commandment.
That's a c-
man. Right? There's just nothing negative about it. Or I could say to you, when you go out there,
you're joy yourself, don't eat too much and make yourself sick. That's a negative commandment.
That's warning you off from something bad. So Adam had not just, right? Here's what fully mature,
complete man looks like.
the future, but he was on a path that led there by doing certain things and not doing another
thing. Right? He had a way of life laid out to him, right, and set before him. Now,
like I said, we've talked before on the show about those two positive commandments, right?
that Genesis is very clear that Eden is not prepared.
Paradise is not the whole world.
Right.
It is a place.
And that when the earth is supposed to be filled with life and subdued and put an order,
right, that a garden like Eden or Paradise is sort of the perfect example of that.
Right.
a garden unlike a bayou is
in good order, right? There's lots of living things in the
value, but they're not in good order, right? A parking lot is in very good
order, but there's no life there, right? Unless, you know, it hasn't been paved
recently, and it's cracking open and life is coming through, is growing up from
underneath it. But when that happens, that disrupts the order of the parking
That's one at the expense of the other.
Where's a garden?
That's a well-tended garden is perfectly in order and because it is in perfect order
It brings forth
Life in greater abundance
Right, so those go together in a garden and so
One way of summarizing Adam's job which he shares with his wife is to turn the whole world into Eden
to expand the boundaries of Eden until it is all created.
creation. And through that process, right, this is what it means that he is to be the image of God,
because we were just told right at the beginning of Genesis 1, that at the beginning of God's creation
the world, the world was formless or disordered or chaotic and empty.
And God proceeded on the six days of creation to put the creation in order and then to fill
it with life for three days, second three days.
We talked about that before.
And so Adam going and filling the world and subdoing it and putting it in order is him
doing what God does.
Him participating in God's work.
gets
extending, you know, to use a Tolkienian term, it is subcreation. Yeah. And in so doing,
he not only would have fulfilled the purpose he was created for, but by serving as the image
of God in creation, he would have become like God. Yeah. And so this is what St. Basil the
the greatest talking about when he says talking about theosis.
that man is the creature who is commanded to become God. And you may be like, well, I miss
that commandment. Right? That commandment. It's not one of the ten. It's not one of the right,
and you flip around trying to find... Well, it's right here in Genesis 2. Right? That's the command.
That's what Phil the Earth did subdue it means.
means to become like God, right? By doing this. And so as we've talked about all the father say,
St. Andrew says, Rhea says all the father say that the devil fell through envy. This is what the envy was based on.
Yeah. Yeah. The devil's envy was based on this destiny of humanity.
This potential of human
This path on which humanity was set, that he was not.
Right. And so, even though,
even though the devil was at the point of creation,
higher up in the hierarchy of creation, right, a greater being, as it were,
right of a higher order. Right.
man was created a little lower than the angels, right? But then, right, has this ability to be
crowned with glory and honor, God's own glory, right? And to be honored by the rest of creation.
And this is what leads the devil to envy and to his attempt to destroy humanity and his fall
in
Genesis 3. But there's also here, right, as this is laid out here in the first
couple chapters of Genesis, there's also a certain mystery. What is that mystery?
Well, how is it possible for humanity to do this? And why is it only possible
for humanity to do this.
Why couldn't the devil become like God in the same way that Adam could have?
Right. I mean, it might be obvious if we're talking about like why a paramecium can't, right? But like,
why can't a seraphim? Why can't a cherubim? Why not the angels? I mean, right? Come on.
Yeah, so there is there is this mystery
It's not gonna go on forever but in the
the first few chapters of Genesis, there's this mystery.
Right.
We will have solved it by the third half of this show.
Yes.
All will be revealed.
You probably figured it out already.
But anyway, this actually revealed yesterday,
liturgically.
But indeed.
So, this is Adam R.
Right, before the fall, right, and what salvation meant for him.
So salvation would have meant for him following those commandments,
becoming like God, becoming mature and complete, being formed into the image of,
of perfect man.
That, that is what salvation meant for him before.
Okay.
So now Adam, false, Adam is expelled from paradise.
His wife becomes Eve, right? The mother of all living. They are now outside of paradise, right?
But, but as the the curses in Genesis 3 make clear, the purpose of humanity, the goal of humanity has not changed.
Yeah, it's still, you know, fill the earth, subdue it.
Do the things that God made out of me for?
Right.
So, woman is still going to give birth, right, and make more people, but now it is going
to be painful and difficult.
Man is still going to put the world into order, similar to by working the ground to bring
forth food, but now it's going to be difficult.
still going to have to work together to do it, but as it says in the curse that's announced
to Eve, it's going to be difficult for them to do that, to work together. Right. So while
the Purpose remains the same, these other elements, these other factors, these four and elements
have now entered in and present obstacles. Right. That stand between humanity and the purpose
for which God created humanity.
And we've talked about those before, but just to make sure we're all on the same page.
So first element is sin, right? Through Adam's sin enters the world.
And then it's crouching at the door waiting for his son, right?
Then because sin has now entered the world, right?
evil is now entered into the world. God says, uh...
It's not good that man should live forever in this state, right?
There are created things that are evil and immortal, they're called demons, right?
So God said, it's not good that humanity become like the demons, right?
And so he brings about death, physical death, meaning we have a mortal life in this world
with the beginning, middle and end.
to allow for repentance, but we still die. So there's now sin and death.
And then the curse that's put on the devil in Genesis chapter 3 is, he's made the Lord of the
dead. He's given the power of death, as Hebrews says. So that power of death, death and the sin
that
requires it and brings it about is wielded against humanity by the devil and other demonic powers
to corrupt and destroy humanity.
So you have sin, death, and the demonic powers, right?
Now, interpose between humanity and the goal for which humanity was created.
And so now, after the expulsion from Paradise,
Will we ask the question?
what does salvation mean for Adam?
At its core, it means the same thing.
It means him growing to maturity and completeness
and the full measure of the perfect man
and becoming like God, but for that to happen,
sin is gonna have to be dealt with,
death is gonna have to be dealt with,
and the demonic powers are gonna have to be dealt with.
Right.
order to make that again possible for humanity.
And so, the next major figure we come to, as we're reading Genesis, who's in the business
of salvation, shall we say, is Noah. Yeah. So, we find Noah. We're out of the world.
the point where as the text says, we read through a couple chapters of the descent of Cain's line,
right? It starts out with Cain the first murderer and goes downhill from there.
Until we're at the point in Genesis 5 and 6, where we're told that everyone on Earth's thoughts
That's where always evil all the time.
Which I mean obviously it's not taking to be absolute you have no but pretty much everybody else
Right yeah, pretty much yeah even even Calvinists don't think people are that bad, okay
Wow
Usually they lean into that
Yeah, no no total of gravity does not mean you are the worst you could possibly be but these people were the worst they could possibly be
They were all they could be unless.
And then we're told that Noah is righteous from his generation.
Meaning he is a, he's fundamentally different.
Right.
And how he lives and what he does, then the rest, the rest of his generation.
Okay.
So what is salvation for Noah?
Well, salvation for Noah is being saved from the rest of humanity.
to be blunt, right? To be saved from the sin and evil that has taken over his world.
Completely, right? From top to bottom. But, but there is a difference here because when you hear about,
We're talking about Genesis in the early chapters, so you're talking about someone being saved from the evils of the world.
You might think of Enic.
And yes, I pronounce it like the sleigh stack.
I don't care. Feel, feel free to post your copy.
Don't care. So I'm going to say Enic.
Um, Enic.
Who Enic is like the one of only a couple people who actually do get raptured in the Bible.
Um, so Enic is sort of removed from
From
the wickedness and evil of the world. That's not what happens with Noah and the reason that's not what happens with Noah
is everybody starts reading the story of Noah with Genesis chapter 6, but he's actually born at the end of chapter 5
and it is birth his father makes a prophecy that the world is going to be saved through Noah.
The creation is going to be saved through Noah.
And so for that to happen, we can't just pluck Noah out.
of the world, right? And let the world continue going, you know, where, right? Because it's
already kind of there. And so instead, right? The answer is, Noah is preserved. The righteous
man is preserved as God, as we talked about in our flood episode, you know, unmakes and remakes
the creation but purifies the creation from sin and cuts off sin.
Put an end to it.
by putting it into all the centers.
Hating the sin and loving the center is a good motto for you and I in this life, but
eventually the chickens come home to roost for the unrepentance.
there. Right. It's so, sin is cut off by everyone be
wiped out, and the waters purify the creation from the sin and the wickedness. And Noah is
preserved and emerges on the other side and is told what?
Well, the earthen subdued it, right?
Start over.
All right.
So once he is saved through the waters, right?
from the sin and evil in the world,
someone like St. Peter might compare that to baptism.
Then on the other side, what is salvation for him?
It's what it was for Adam, right?
You're originally, right?
It's becoming like God,
being conformed to the measure of the perfect man, right?
That salvation for him on the other side,
once he's been saved from that.
but there's still a problem.
Right. Sin is still around.
Right. See ham.
Sin is still around.
Death is certainly still around.
Right. The flood doesn't deal with death. In fact, the flood is used death to deal with sin.
Yeah.
Right. Death is first put into place human death at least in in Genesis chapter three
to deal with them.
right in the sense of putting a limit on sin by limiting human life spans but also
but also to
I forgot what he also was
but so nothing's put into place to deal with sin
Steven. Yeah, I know. I know.
Maybe this is what await me in two months. I guess this is
What awaits me in two months when I found a little catch up to your current age?
I'm sure all that time you spent sleeping at night doesn't count.
So you'll probably be.
No, so that's the original purpose of death is to cut off sin, right?
And to create repentance from sin by the knowledge of death.
That's where I was going with it.
this is sort of an extremist death being used to deal with.
to deal with sin.
So the next figure we get, there's not really one single figure.
You may be thinking we're going to the Tower of Babel next, but there's not sort of a righteous man at the center of the Tower of Babel story.
Unless, and we're not going down this rabbit hole tonight, potentially another time we will.
Unless it's Abraham himself at the Tower of Bable, which there's a rich Jewish...
literature about that idea. But the next figure we get is Abraham. The next
righteous man we meet is Abraham. And so we meet Abraham in Ura. He's living in
Ura of the Caldees. He's living in a world. I mean it's the Samaritan
Renaissance as we've talked about before you can go back and listen to the
Abraham episode. He's living at the height of...
Earth's civilization thus far up to that point. But there's a big giant
Ziggurat built in the center of the city during his lifetime. It's a temple to
a pagan god. Right. And so we know that even in his own household there are
people who are bound to these demonic powers, masquerading his gods. He lives
in a world that is...
just corrupt like this. And while the separating of the nations, we've talked about how at
Babel, we sort of get this picture that things are descending quickly toward the point they
were before the flood. Right? We have Nimrod show up who sort of our token Nephilim, right? We have
people becoming evil again, doing great evil things, it got sort of scattered as the nations,
And that kind of puts off the descent of the whole world.
to total evil, but only puts it off. Right? Things aren't moving in a positive direction.
They're just maybe moving a little more slowly. So what is salvation for Abraham? Well,
in his own life, part of it is being called out of that world.
Yeah, I mean, that's kind of the big turning point moment in the life of Abraham as God comes to
and says time to go.
Yeah, it's time to leave this city.
Right.
The city with the ziggurat in the middle, that's a pagan temple.
The city devoted to a pagan god, where a demon holds sway.
Right.
To get away from that, to go out to another land, to live nomatically, right, to remove
himself from that whole lifestyle.
And in the context of that,
Abraham receives these two promises or these promises that have set of promises that have two prongs
Right
One of them is he's going to have descendants
It's going to have lots of them
This quantity
But then there's also a promise about his descendants
Regarding quality that they will shine like the stars of heaven
Yeah, three buses.
stars and multiplies the sands of the sea.
Yes. And so he's also promised, right, this particular chunk of land, right. And that
land to which he is brought in which as many descendants will dwell, not nomadically,
more permanently, not permanently, but more permanently.
Then Abraham did. Then serves as this sign, when you see these things accomplished, then
you will know that the rest of the promise is true regarding becoming like the stars of
heaven. And as we talked about in the Abraham episode, when you said stars of heaven to
Someone from OOR, they were thinking of gods.
Yeah, yeah. What we would call angelic beings, right, because we get sketchy about gods in the plural, right?
That's what they would think about. So when you're saying you're just saying it's going to be like them,
this is a re-iteration of the promise. This is a re-iteration of the promise,
of man's destiny, that through Abraham and his seed.
Right that original purpose for which humanity was created is going to be accomplished
and
Right within the context of those promises
It is implied
That sin and death and the powers the demonic powers are going to be dealt with
How is that implied right? Well, it's implied in
And first of all, it's obviously in that.
Humanities going to be restored to its original purpose, right?
Which as we said, those service barriers, but also, it's critically important to remember
Isaac, special significance of Isaac.
Not only is Isaac the seed of Abraham in a singular way, right?
So Abraham had a bunch of sons, right?
Suns
had father Abraham back. I am. So are you. Not in this sense. I mean, literally,
right? Biologically, it's not even just Isaac and Ishmael. There were more. Yeah,
yeah, after Sarah died. So he had a bunch of sons, right? And they had sons, they became
whole nations, right? But there is also this singular Sun.
The singular son, this singular son represents a kind of singular hope.
And people jump really quickly to, oh, well, he's the one who's going to receive the promises.
Well, no, we've talked about this before on the show several times.
Actually, all of those kids received parts of the promises.
parts of the land.
right? So his grandson Esau isn't Jacob isn't the first born but still gets part of the land that was promised Abraham
See Deuteronomy chapter 2
right
Right
So they receive that promise
That means by the way since that is the sign that they also have opened to them the promise of salvation
They're still human. They're still in the image of God
So that salvation that goes all the way back to the creation of Adam is also open to them,
even though they're not going to be quote unquote Israelites.
So there's that singular element, but we also have to remember that that singular element,
Isaac, the singular son, right, the one who's going to have this special role, right?
So the first born is the one who had
administered the inheritance, right? But the other sons also, when dealt with justly received an inheritance,
comes from a womb that the tax describes as dead.
Sarah's womb as an extremely elderly woman is described as being dead.
But that is where Isaac comes from.
So that life, that hope, that one...
who's going to administer the inheritance,
that singular seed, right, overcomes death,
Isaac overcomes death by coming into existence.
Yeah.
Which is a sign, right?
That death itself is going to be overcome.
And if death itself is gonna be overcome,
that means the purpose for it existing
will have to be overcome.
and the demonic powers who...
wield it will have to be overcome. Right? That's sort of that's what I mean by. It implies that
that will be taken care of. Yeah, so the defeat of sin and demons is implied in the defeat of death.
Right. Yeah, cool. So if you can remember all the way back to the beginning of this podcast,
Many suffer so much younger than this.
I had so much hope.
humanity in the future. That's all. No. Well, it is all gone now, but it was gone a long
time ago. I've been running on fumes since like sixth grade. So we said not only are we
going to talk about what salvation is, right? We've been talking about that for Adam and Noah
and Abraham. What salvation was. We also said we were going to talk about how you receive
Yeah right.
right? How it comes to you, right? Because as we see with Adam right off the bat, the fact
that God created Adam for a particular purpose toward a particular end, even in motion toward
a particular end, did not guarantee that Adam would achieve that end. Likewise, no, likewise,
Abraham, right? And so what is the key in all three cases?
The key in all three cases we can clearly see, and St. Paul will fill you in very quickly if you don't notice this yourself, is faithfulness.
The way Adam would have received salvation, the way he would have been conformed to the likeness of perfect man, the way he would have become like God, and those are the same thing, even though it's mysterious as to how.
The way he would have done that was by being faithful in keeping the three commandments
he was given by faithfully following the way of life that God had set before him to
do these things and not do that thing.
Right?
Noah gets told about the flood, has prophesied that the world is going to be saved through
him.
But what does he have to do to receive that?
That means that he spends 100 years building a boat.
I mean, probably way over budget too.
Yes.
So, not to harp too much on our Calvinist friends,
but we can clearly see the salvation in the case of Adam
and Noah's not monogistic in either case.
All right, they have to do a thing.
have to do a thing.
Yeah, God does it build the boat for him. He closes the door, but he does it build the boat for him.
Right.
Um, and so then Abraham,
how does he receive salvation, faithfulness? He doesn't just sit in or and say, yes, God,
I believe you that I will have many children and they will all live in that land and they will become like the stars of heaven.
I'm totally on board.
Right.
And God, I've got this to him.
Not righteous.
Now I've got this game of the, the real game of Error to get back to.
Hey, how did you know what I was to play it online?
No, you know, yeah.
So that's what I assume you're doing through most of these episodes.
You're just, you know, you hear me going want, want, want, want, want, want,
and you just real game of work.
No, it's time for a.
Yeah.
Um.
that I read off a Bible quote, there's a long pause and then you come in and read it.
Oh, yes, yes, quick clip on me online. So, uh, you were able to say, if they write, he,
he does what God tells him to do. Right. Now, someone out there may object.
Someone from any number of backgrounds may object and say, hold on a second.
St. Paul said Abraham believed and it was credited to him as righteousness. Yeah
So I guess like in Putee's you know, even though he did actually go like he he didn't actually have to
And that yes and that God just he believes that God just says okay, you're righteous. You're perfect or whatever right like you're done
you're there.
But that's reading a ton of things into the text.
First of all, believed, right, is the word
that we're translating faithfulness.
So what St. Paul really says is Abraham was faithful
and God credited him as righteous.
And that credited, probably more like a wrecking.
Right?
Yeah, he was faithful.
Oh, oh, yes, that's righteousness.
Yes.
So what they pause doing there is
He's telling you the standard by which Abraham was reckoned to be righteous.
Okay, so if I say to you, right, that, you know, my friend, Pete VanderVene is tall.
You're gonna hear the Dutch last name and believe me.
But if I say, right.
He's really tall.
You might say, unless if we're out in an old late night show,
you'd be like, how tall is he?
How tall is he?
No.
But you guys say, well, what do you mean tall?
Yeah.
Tall compared to who?
Tall compared to what?
Right?
Because, you know, in a person in certain countries,
I don't want to get myself a too much.
trouble here, but a person in certain countries who's like six two would be considered tall,
maybe even really tall. In the Netherlands, six two is like your 13.
Right? Like someone in the Netherlands who's like six seven would be considered tall,
really tall. Right? You got it, you got it because there's a higher average height. Right?
So you've got to say,
using a comparative like that, they say, compared to what? Or by what standard? Right? So if you're
going to say somebody's a righteous dude, right? You've got to have some kind of standard. It might be
what the what the cool kids at the high school say. Right? In this case, we're told that the standard
by which God reckons of the righteous is that he was faithful to what God called him to do.
And not that he is the sausage king.
of Chicago. Yeah, that's all that that's saying. That's all that that's saying. There is no
complex, there's no judicial language there. Yeah. I know you want there to be some of you guys.
Right. Um, by the way, if you, if you want to take quote unquote justification as forensic language
that he's being declared righteous.
To be perfectly righteous, then...
happens to him twice because it happens at Genesis 15 and again in chapter 22.
And in both cases when he does something but that's right so don't don't read too much into that
right? That's the standard right but as we said that's a standard for everybody we've seen so far
at Genesis. That's a standard for Adam that's a standard for Noah that's standard for Abraham. Are
Are they faithful in what God calls them to-
do, right, in the life, the way of life that he puts before them. Are they faithful to it or not?
Right, and if they are, they make progress, right, to spite the problems of sin and death and the devil,
right, toward being conformed to the likeness of God to the perfect man. And if they
are faithless than they make the opposite of progress.
In that regard, huh?
All right, well we're gonna go ahead and take our first break and we'll be right back
and get your calls here on this episode of the Laura Spears Podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen De Young will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
Let's eat 5 5 a f
Radio.
Ancient Near Eastern texts such as the Bale Cycle portray the pagan god Bale as a rebel.
The hero of a revolution worshipped and glorified for his long string of victories.
In the Bale Book, a biography of the devil, Father Stephen the Young shows that the Hebrew
scriptures consciously turn the Bale story on its head.
Depicting him as a failed and defeated rebel who nonetheless tries to steal the glory that
belongs to.
Almighty God. From these scriptures the figure of the devil emerged within Jewish and Christian tradition.
Father Stephen works through the old and new testament passages that refer to various
bail stories and he surveys bail worship through followers' beliefs, religious practices,
and liturgical life to show that the figures of bail and the devil, the Prince of Demons,
are one in the same. You can find the bail book at store.hentfaith.com. That's store.hentfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Hey, welcome back, everybody.
How you like that?
And their father, we got a voiceover saying the bail book rather than the...
Yeah, so yeah.
and no disrespect.
The speaker of the previous commercial that I do like the bail pronunciation better
I do wonder why you recorded this one at a disco tech in Brussels
I wonder why you have so much knowledge of disco techs in Brussels
I bet some people in the YouTube chat have knowledge of disco techs and Brussels
So we actually have a bunch of collars and
and uh
I'm feeling a little wild tonight.
They're not, I don't, maybe one of them is somewhat on topic,
but I'm just gonna go ahead and let these,
let three people through.
Are you cool with that, Father?
Yes.
Let's all do what is right in our own eyes.
That's right, that's right.
So okay, well, our first caller is John from Missouri.
John, welcome to Laura Spirits podcast.
Hey, Father, the long time caller first time listener.
Yeah, yeah, we've heard that one.
before we do. It's possibly true. It can't be a long time collar. What does that even mean?
Like we've been talking for eight seconds. He could be somebody you could be somebody who
heard about me on the internet and was just in rage is like I need to call in at a guy.
Even though I never listen to his show. When is it on? Is that the case? John from Missouri?
Perhaps.
Oh.
Okay, let's give you a little cagey.
What's on your mind out there?
So this is going on the Julia and Latria discussion.
So like I agree with you guys,
like you know, worship involves a sacrifice,
but John is rebuked by the angel in the book of Revelation
for what is like, it says it's worship.
I don't know if there's like a translation kind of thing
going on and does that mean there's like a veneration issue
that's our veneration that's only forgot alone.
and could you elaborate on that?
Yes. I think we covered this in our Angel of the Lord episode, which now is years ago.
I think maybe was at the end of 2021, maybe?
I think so.
It's time for the flat circle.
I don't know.
I know.
Yeah. So yeah, as I recall, I don't have the Greek text in front of me. But as I recall,
what it says is that he'd be bowed down in front of him. Like that's what it literally,
I think it used...
is proskeenesis actually. So he's clearly not pulling out animals or bread or wine or anything
like that to offer a sacrifice. So then the question would be, why does the angel stop
him from doing that? And as I recall, it's because it's to let John know that this is not
the angel of the Lord. In other words, this is not the Son of God.
even though venerating an angel in and of itself is not a bad thing.
But that John might have thought, oh, I'm in the presence of Christ here.
Because I mean, here's the thing.
If bowing down in front of someone should only be given to God, then what about all the
other times in the scriptures when other people bow down and no one calls them idolaters?
You know, there's a lot of frustration going on.
David and Jonathan do that with-
each other. No one calls them my doletars. There's a lot of stuff where people fall down in front of
other people and bow down in front of them. Right? So clearly this angel is not saying to John,
no, no, you must only prostrate in front of God because that's just not been a thing up to that
point. So the only context that makes sense is that John was mistaking him for the angel of the Lord
and he was letting him know, no, no, just just get up. Come on, we got somewhere to go.
So.
doing the whole psychopomp thing as he's taking him on a visionary tour. Am I
remember correctly father? Is that what we basically said in that episode? Yeah, I
mean roughly yeah, because St. John sees Christ in several different forms or images
right in his vision, right? He sees, there's with bronze skin and white hair and
he sees the lamb, right? And he's right, so he's seeing angels, he's seeing Christ in
different.
imagery, right, in his vision.
And so it's about clarifying who he is.
Larger point, though, once again, is we, and by we here, I mean like the Orthodox Church
historically, are not making a claim that the words worship and veneration or any particular
Greek words or Latin words or Siri words, translated into the same one.
or use this technical terms everywhere in scripture and everywhere in the
fathers. Right. Right. Right. The point is that you're taking not the words
that are used. Those words are just labels to put on the distinction. So we
could say there is a that you offer to God alone, which is primarily
sacrifice, there is B which you offer to F.
everyone as it is due to them. Right? Including God, but also including glorified
humans, angels, other living humans, your parents, right, etc. etc. We can just call them
A and B, right? To make that distinction. Right? So yeah, there's, I think a lot of people
seem to think that we're saying no, this is like...
definitional to this word in English or in Greek.
And so then, you know, they come to the Sunday,
the Holy Cross and they hear before that cross,
we bow down in worship and they're like,
ah, I caught you, you're doing it idolatry, right?
And we're not claiming these are technical terms.
These are fluid terms in English,
they're fluid terms in Greek.
We're just using them as labels because you have to do something.
You better get to A and B.
or one and two, right?
You have to, when you make a distinction,
you have to identify somehow the two things
you're distinguishing.
Yeah.
So, is that clear things after you, John and Missouri?
Or do you find us hopelessly idolatrous?
I don't.
I mean, I hope you're not idolatrous
because I do a lot of this out of venerate.
And that's like, I don't really want to go to L.
So I'd be a bummer.
That would be a bummer.
I feel like we should have someone clip what you just said, John.
And just play that every so often. I don't want to go, oh, that would be a bummer.
That's the best thing I've heard all day. Perhaps the ultimate bummer.
Yes. The last of all bummer.
Yeah, what could be worse? So all right. Well, thank you very much for calling, John. God bless you.
All right. Thank you very much.
Yep, yep, yep. Okay, our next call is
Think of it. Think of it. Think of it this way, dude
listener, right? You've got a hamichee sandwich, you've got a hot dog, right? Those are two different things.
You can come and say, is not a hot dog also kind of a sandwich? It's people doing bread, right?
And it would be like, okay, yes, but we both know that the hot dog and the hamichee sandwich are two
different things. So just let me make my distinction. Right exactly. Part of the problem, of course, is that
that people don't seem to feel this deep.
down, but like the English word worship, for most of its history has meant venerate, which
is why I think I mentioned this before in the show that even today judges in the UK and
Princess Leia in Star Wars are referred to as your worship.
And the Anglican wedding service that couple each say to each other with my body, I the
the worship.
So they're definitely not offering sacrifices to each other, treating the other one like a God.
They're, they're saying, I, I venerate you.
So yeah, the point is, what is the action?
What is the action action?
I have some bad news for you, Father Andrew.
What's that other than yourself?
I don't think anyone feels English,
an apology deep in their bones.
I really am going home now.
Yeah.
I'm going to go home and pray like Elijah that the Lord just takes your life because you're the only one left to appreciate.
Everyone else is bowed the knee to the
recency to modern usage. That's right.
Okay, so our next caller is Joseph from Nevada. So welcome Joseph. Welcome to Lord of Spirits podcast.
Do we have you?
Joseph from Nevada.
Oh, I'm sorry.
Father's bless.
I was on mute.
Just wanted to raise his objection from playing devil's
advocate.
The presence is going to say, well, all this stuff won't
renovate and worship and all this stuff.
But not for salvation.
This is going to say, but not for salvation.
Go to church, read the Bible, but not for salvation.
For what then?
I mean that's the thing
honestly that question is part of why I left Protestantism really like I had a
sense of like the kind now I mean there's a lot of different kinds of
Protestantism don't at me I literally have a 400 page book basically saying that
but but in the version of Protestantism that I was in we believed in one
state always saved right so I had done the thing I had had the moment and I had
gotten saved.
And so since I had that, then one of the big questions that eventually kind of occurred to me was
Why am I doing all this other stuff? Why is all this other stuff important? It feels important. It seems important
I wanted to be important, but what is it actually for?
And
the best kinds of answers that I could get were something like well it contributes to your growth
Which okay, but like hey, I've got heaven in the bag so
You know, what does that even mean?
buddy, you know, more crowns in the hereafter. How many crowns can one man cast down anyway?
So yeah, it was because of a sense that, that doctrinally speaking, at least within my, you know,
my frame, that all those other things weren't really actually important,
that they didn't critically matter. So that's what I would say to that. And why would, you know,
know why wouldn't Christ, why would all the apostles, why would the prophets constantly
urging people to faithfulness if it didn't really matter.
Absolutely. I mean, I have so much more of a sense of purpose now. I mean, like there's
actually a purpose for all the things that we're doing. And if salvation is the purpose,
then that's a full Christian life. Not just think of a symbolic thing, like the sanctification
the growth thing then just becomes memorial and not
realistic. Yeah. Yeah. So my call board says that you had another question about the one
that Father Stephen calls Enic. Yes, just the passing one. Yes. They're going to use
that as a type and shadow of the rapture and I actually had kind of an eye opening moment
as I was waiting. I'm a former mechanic. I'm not ethnically Jewish, but I was kind of raised
around my life in Israel and all this type of stuff. So I kind of had the revelation.
that this whole dispensationalist rapture deal
is just so that they could create another covenant
and do the judyizing thing on this earth
and replace the church, which is that function preservation.
I kind of had that eye opening.
I hope I'm articulating it right, but like yeah.
But the question is how to respond to that.
That that's a type of rapture.
That Enoch being, I'm sorry, Enic.
I need it.
I can't do it.
Enoch being, you know,
school watch some land of the lost.
You'll get into that.
Being taken is a,
it's a pre-wrap sure it's a rapture preview.
Yeah. Pretty what do you think?
That's Stephen.
Why didn't make them joke.
But yeah, the,
in terms of the,
it is which as you say,
they do seem, you know,
just dead set on helping the
Antichrist build the third time.
What is that? What is that all about?
Especially right really you read
Reed St. John of Damascus besides exposition of the Orthodox faith where he talks about the
Antichrist rebuilding the
Jewish temple of being worshiped in it.
Give me the he be jeepies about our dispensationalist friends like
like, guys, yeah, and it is a weird...
I don't think it's fair to Judyizers to call them Judyizers.
Isn't that sad that I have more sympathy for Judyizers than for them?
Judyizers are responsible for fewer deaths.
Because they don't really
They basically fetishize Jewish people?
Yeah.
Which is, I mean, we, we, we Jewish people by the way, find really creepy.
Yeah. I mean, this morning when we were doing our briefing for this episode,
Father Stephen and I were discussing making a big list of all the things that modern Orthodox Jews do,
that would weird out the particular set of like evangelicals and dispensationalists who fetishize that.
Yeah.
You know, like we're like, they go and pray at the tomb of Abraham, you know, fun stuff like that.
Yeah, but yeah, so it's.
So basically I'm kind of I guess saying no to your question, but the
to provide so that I think it's actually worse than you're suggesting.
Yeah, and it's a deeply steeped political ideology, meaning it's about violence primarily.
Yeah.
Yep.
And where to direct it.
All right.
Well, I hope that helps Joseph.
Yes.
Thank you.
Great.
That's exactly why you left.
Thanks.
Great.
Thank you.
Alright.
Yeah, we're gonna take one more call.
Uh, and uh, this is, this is Josh who's calling from Ann Arbor, Michigan.
So Josh, welcome to the Spirit's podcast.
Hello, Father's bless.
God bless you. You made it in. You sound vaguely relieved.
It's true. I tried before but didn't quite make it.
I know. Sometimes Mike just randomly hangs up on people.
You know, Mike again, what can we say about that guy?
He just starts hitting the button and he just doesn't want to deal with callers, you know.
I get that a lot to be honest.
I'm thinking about docking his vacation time just because it would be fun.
He gets vacation time.
Yeah, we're very nice employer to work for actually.
I thought you had him shackled to the the board.
He shackles himself.
I mean, this guy's sleep.
He sleeps in the studio.
The great thing is he can't answer us right now.
But I know you have, I'm so aware.
to go. Yeah, there we go. That's true. You don't pay him enough to have a place to live.
You know, that's trying to throw him out of there at night. He's like, I need a place to sleep.
So he just handcuffs himself to the board. That's right. All right. Sorry, Josh.
We're just, you know, I, you know, I, for whatever reason, I've been remiss in making fun of,
you know, giving creative nicknames to Mike DeGanne over the last couple episodes. We have
to kind of make up for that a little bit, you know. Otherwise, his priest told us that he would
remove his blessing frame to work for.
So I'm trying to keep him employed. That's really what it'll be completely out of that. That's right. That's right. That's right
So what's what's what's up there in Michigan that's on your mind?
Well, I made a former PSA believer and so my question is about Isaiah 53. I understand you lead the
group version generally.
But you kind of break it up but we heard you.
I heard you read the Greek version.
Right, the true version by the day of 5310.
Does it yet it was the will of the Lord to crush him?
So you're asking, is that not penal substitute scenario tonement?
It just sounds like it's something that the father is doing against the son.
What do you think, what do you think, Father Stephen, is that indeed?
have you know the older we have a god older
He was, he was pleased to crush him.
But all that, all that means is that what happened to Christ was God's will.
Yeah.
Something the father did against him.
Yeah. I mean, it's not like, I mean, imagine, right?
We'll also imagine like, you know, the father's up there like grinning.
Well, no, yeah, I know.
So the two to crush him part, right?
It was his will to crush him.
When you see the word two like that,
that's an infinitive in English.
Yeah, right?
Because it's translating an infinitive construct form in Hebrew,
right?
But an infinitive is just the verb,
sort of in its simplest state.
So, um, the, the you could translate it as easily crushing him was his will or his being
crushed even because there's no, there's no tense to an infinitive.
And the infinitive does not have a subject or a direct object.
The crushing of him. It's just considering the action in and of itself. The crushing of him was God's will.
But you want to do a wouldnly literal translation of the Hebrew. His being crushed was God's will.
And that's right. The Garden of Gassamini.
Yeah, not my will but done not my will but then be done
Father's tell us, you know, six-eccumenical counsel, that's the my will there is the, as Christ's
human will, the divine will, right, which Christ shares with the Father and the Spirit, right?
Meaning all three persons of the Trinity, it was their will, it was their plan, right, that
Christ be crushed.
that what happened to him in his crucifixion happened.
Yeah, and I mean, the thing is, Penal substitutionary atonement,
in its true sense, has a bunch of very specific
parts to it. I think a part of the problem with people pointing at stuff is that they assume that model
right, and then they see something that looks like it's one piece of it and they say,
the rest of the model must be there.
You know, the idea that it was the will of God that Christ should die.
Does not imply the whole rest of the penal sub-stutionary atonement model.
Right. You also have to ask so when if we're doing exegesis if we're trying to determine
what is this verse this verse in Isaiah teaching.
Okay.
Uh, how would I, how would I say a B.
setting forth in an atonement model.
Right. Like you would have to argue here Isaiah is explaining to
everyone how right like the mechanism of or part of the
mechanism in this case, it's only part of it part of the
mechanism by which God is going to justify
sinners without them actually not being sinners.
Yeah, and I mean, and also just a few verses
before that one, right?
We have a verse that gets explicitly interpreted
in the gospels where it says he is born our griefs
and carried our sorrows.
Isn't it in Matthew's gospel?
I can't recall.
Yeah, he says that was fulfilled when Christ healed people.
Right.
Not fulfilled when, you know,
Don't forget to subscribe and hit the bell icon so you don't miss any videos.
filled when Christ was crucified actually. But when he healed people. Right. But more importantly,
more importantly, because it talks about him bearing our infirmities, right? And St. Matthew is
clearly not saying like when when Christ healed a paralyzed person, he became paralyzed, right?
Or when he healed a blind person, he became blind or he healed a leper, he got leprosy,
right he's talking about he's
He's purifying them of leprosy.
He's healing them.
So when that same language is applied to sin,
why would we interpret it differently
than St. Matthew interprets it?
Yeah.
Right.
That it means Christ taking away sin,
purifying people from sin,
cleansing them from sin, healing them from sin.
It would mean the same thing.
But so it doesn't make sense for Isaiah to be
like just throwing out pieces of an atonement model
Little prof
700 years before Christ died, right? But what does make sense, right, allow me to
suggest, is the idea that the because the servant is also talking about Israel
there. It's not talking about Israel, it's instead of the Messiah. Part of why
Jesus is the Messiah is that he embodies Israel and recapitulates Israel, right,
that the software
sufferings of Israel, the sufferings of the Israelites people, and in its ultimate fulfillment,
the sufferings of Christ are all according to God's knowledge and plan.
Meaning God's people don't suffer, and ultimately Christ didn't suffer because God couldn't
stop it from happening.
It wasn't a surprise.
It was something over.
power to overwhelm the God. Right? Like the Assyrians thought their gods had beaten the
God of Israel when they conquered Israel. The Babylonians thought Marduk had conquered
the God of Israel when they conquered Israel. Right? So, contextually, Isaiah has every
reason to be talking about that, that this didn't happen outside the will of God, that
God has a purpose for it.
God is going to bring good out of it.
Right? And it then makes sense for the New Testament writers to take that and apply that to Christ as the ultimate fulfillment where it's filled to overflowing.
Because this is the ultimate evil.
Right? It flipped it on God himself.
And yet it is part of God's plan and God brings the greatest good possible out of it.
Yeah.
Yep, which of those is it makes sense for Isaiah to be talking about?
This is like the Roman...
problem with a lot of Calvinist proof texts and Romans is they first have to justify why
is St. Paul writing to the church in Rome to describe some abstract theological principles
to them? Is it more likely he's writing them to address some issues they're actually facing
like he does in all of his epistles?
So there's a framing question that we have to answer before.
we start trying to do exegesis.
Yep.
Does that make sense, Josh?
That makes sense.
Thank you.
All right.
You broke up there, but I'm going to go ahead and fill in what you...
It sounded like that makes absolute perfect sense.
You guys are geniuses.
Thank you.
Right?
Is that basically what you said?
Exactly.
Yep.
All right.
Great.
Thanks for coming, Josh.
All right.
It's the second half.
We're not gonna start with Genesis this time, but with, with, with actually that would be weird if we started the second half with
Genesis. Oh, we've probably done that. We probably, there's at least one episode I'm sure where we start in the stone age in the first half. Yes. And then like second half is Genesis. I'm sure we've done that at least once. Yeah. Yeah.
Moses Moses.
Yes, now we're getting to Moses, who as we mentioned before,
It poses its toes as it roses.
But Moses supposedly is erroneously.
For Moses, he knows his toes are roses as he
supposedly is to be.
I feel like you're really living some moment of your childhood there.
No, this is actually another Danny K reference,
which is becoming a theme on the show now.
Wow.
Wait, are you saying that Danny K was not a part of your childhood?
Like, at least on TV.
I'll be a little bit.
not a huge part. Okay. I mean, not like Charles Nelson Riley or something.
Low key he was. So yes, this brings us to Moses. We've moved from Genesis to Exodus in a whole
half of the show. So you may be thinking, Oh, now we're going to talk about Salvation of the Torah.
I say hold your horses friend
We need to talk about Moses himself first.
Right?
Moses is the person.
What is salvation for Moses, the person?
So, the first part of his life,
the first 80 years or so,
is essentially a sort of recapitulation of the life of Abraham,
if you think about it.
Right, so
Abraham when we meet him is an or number one city number one civilization in the
world at the apex of human civilization and Moses ends up in Egypt which at
the time he's alive is one of if not the most but depend on not doing the
day to the axis. Several civilizations in the world right apex of human
civilization, right? He's right there in it. But
It is under the control of the gods of Egypt who are demonic powers who get judged in the Passover, remember.
And so Moses ends up facing potentially a death sentence because he murders the Egyptian.
He goes on the Lamb, so he leaves that civilization.
he goes out into the wilderness and he lives as a nomadic herdsman.
The way Abraham left Ur.
and went and became a nomadic herdsman.
So there is an element of salvation from the powers and potentially from sin and death in
terms of if he had gotten caught for murder in Moses' early life, right, those obstacles.
But what we see with salvation for Moses then in sort of the third activist life, the
last 40 years is
something of a return to form. What is what is salvation for Moses in that part of his life? Well, it is
speaking to God face to face. It is seeing God.
Right. Seeing God. He has made as God to Pharaoh. Right. So he becomes like God. He sees God.
Right. And there aren't a whole pile of people who see God. Right.
And if we're talking about in the Torah, you've basically got four.
You've got Moses and you've got Abraham, Isaac and Jacob.
Yeah, that's pretty much it.
And you may not have thought about this, but you know, why do we get the
list Abraham, Isaac and Jacob? And there's not like Joseph or Judah or somebody on the end there.
None of the 12 patriarchs, none of the sons of...
of Israel, of Jacob, saw God.
Joseph had an interpreted dreams.
But Abraham Isaac and Jacob all saw God directly.
It spoke with him, right, wrestled with him in one case.
And Moses does on Mount Sinai.
And so the core of this
is that those four are our first biblical saints, the way we in the church use the term
saint. They are four people who have achieved that purpose for which humans were created, who
have faithfully moved in that direction.
And so now,
stand in the presence of God and continue.
Right down that path
toward
the image of the perfect man toward the likeness of God.
Right.
So that's true for Moses, the person.
But then of course, Moses gives the Torah.
Right. God gives it through Moses, you should say.
Right. God gives the Torah through Moses.
The Torah is now given to the people of Israel.
as Israel is formed. And so we need to talk about, if we're going to talk about salvation and the Torah,
we've got to talk about sort of three levels of the Torah, three levels at which the Torah functions.
Shall we say? And we're going to talk about these in us ending order. So we're going to start with
with sort of the lowest here.
of the Torah, and then we're going to ascend. Seems appropriate. Seems St. Gregory of
Nisayish. So sort of the lowest level at which the Torah functions has to do with the
land. Because remember, the land was promised to Abraham as a sign. He was brought
into the land himself.
dwell in it as a nomad, as a sign that it would be given to his descendants, but it was
being given to his descendants as a sign of the greater promise, right, of salvation in the
original sense, the original Adam theosis sense. So it's given to, it was going to be given to them
as a sign. And now, as the Torah is given, Israel is being given its peace.
Because remember, eat them already had its peace. Moab already had its peace.
And the other Abrahamites already had their pieces of the land.
Israel is the one who shows up last, right?
They're being given their piece of the land.
But that giving of the land by God as an inheritance to Israel is pre-Tora.
Meaning Israel isn't given the Torah, commanded to keep it.
They keep it for some period.
of time perfectly and then God gives them the land.
Right. No, that's not how it happened. Yeah. He doesn't give them the Torah in Egypt and they
keep it and so he brings them out of Egypt, right? They're brought out of Egypt and brought to the land
before the Torah. Okay. So it is not conditional to them receiving the Torah or receiving the land.
The Torah is not conditional to them receiving the land.
How is the land received?
And to understand even what that question means maybe, we need to step back and look at something,
which is that we're told in Deuteronomy 2 about the other Abrahamites haven't been given their portions of the land promised to their father Abraham.
Israel comes last. We don't get all those gritty details, we're just told that that happens. That happened, right, that they drove out the certain giant clans and were given the land by God.
God and it was...
theirs as part of the inheritance for Maybrah. In Joshua we get the gritty details of what
happens with Israel in particular and the 12 tribes in particular. And so on one hand
we have, like in Numbers, everybody's favorite book of the Bible, we should do like a year-long
numbers study. I kind of did. Yeah, yeah, it's playing right.
right now on the yeah it's right now it's playing on that podcast that is what some of
these people want just you be rambling yes it's a cure for insomnia I mean you gotta
give it that yeah someone in the someone in the chat no no not in the traction on Facebook
said that I do power nap during this show but I can say right right in my sleep apparently
So, just putting that out there.
I don't think Father Andrew actually power an app during the show.
because if he did power an app during the show if he was able to do that we wouldn't have to start so early so we could get to bed.
That seems fair.
Tough but fair.
So we get these gritty details about the 12 tribes.
And in numbers, we get laid out, okay, not just this tribe, but this clan and this tribe, this family, they get these pieces of land.
and it's laid out very particularly, right?
And
those pieces of land are supposed to not only be given to each of those families, but
there's supposed to stay in those families.
Remember, it all reverts in the year of Jubilee if they had celebrated that.
And then we read Joshua and we see that Israel was not exactly batting a thousand in terms
of taking possession of exactly that land.
Right.
They think a lot of it, some tribes more of it, some less of their
parcels, right? Some like Dan, just say forget about it and go and take a different parcel.
Yeah. They like their allotment. So they yeah. So, right, all these things happen, right? And
you're like, well, that's that's messy and weird. So, and you might get to the end of Joshua and be like,
yes, it doesn't sound like they actually got the land of God promised them.
And then at the end of the book of Joshua it says they got all the
and God promised to them. So there's not one promised Abraham that wasn't fulfilled right
there at the end of Joshua. None left. Sorry, dispensationalists. Like they're really
are just proof, proof texts at the end of the book of Joshua that destroy dispensationalism.
Like it's insane. Especially since dispensationalists are all about like we need to read the
Bible literally, literally says all the promises to Abraham were fulfilled.
in the second millennium BC. Now you're going to allegorize. But we want to launch missiles
of people. Yeah, we want to kill people. And this is a good excuse. There's plenty of
other excuses. People have been killing people throughout human history, right? Yeah,
without mystery. They didn't always use the Bible as an excuse. In fact, it's relatively
rare. So the...
But so that seems it odds to us, right?
You can almost forgive the Zionists
because of the cognitive dissonance.
I mean, almost.
Right? In that, right? On one hand, you read, okay.
This letter is being given to these people.
And then on the other hand,
here's the letter that those people actually received
and there's not a matchup, right?
the way in case anyone is
wondering, the reference to Joshua is Joshua 2315. So just there it is, by the way,
everybody. Yeah. Well, is that the Orthodox study Bible or? No, you know, I don't,
I don't know it. The verseification is different in the Orthodox study Bible. Yeah, no, this is
so that's I just want to clarify for people most Bibles. Everybody else is Bible. Yeah,
your dispensationalists will be using that Bible. So not the only next table. Right, right.
That's theversification to go by.
So, and the key there, the bridges that gap is faithfulness.
Right? Faithfulness. Because God said, here is the land that I am giving you.
Here is your inheritance. Right? And then he doesn't just say, there you go.
Just like he didn't say there you go.
go to Abraham. Abraham had to get up and move to the other side of the known world.
Noah had his bed a hundred years building about, right?
He says to them, go take it.
I will be with you.
You will be victorious.
You'll be successful.
Go take it.
Right.
And some of them went and took it.
Some of them didn't.
Yeah.
And those who were faithful,
received their inheritance and those that were not did not.
Right.
This
This is a critically important paradigm related to salvation.
If you don't understand this, you won't understand Romans.
Because as we're going to talk about the third half, spoilers, Christ accomplishes a lot
of things on behalf of all humanity, not just some, not just a select or elect few.
We have of all humanity, but all humanity does not receive those things.
that Christ accomplished because they aren't faithful. Yeah. Right. And so the same thing is true
here. So God can say that He kept all His promises. Right. The example I use this morning, and this
is a very up-to-date, up-to-the-minute example, if you get a phone call saying you want a free VCR,
You just have to go down to the mall and pick it up.
What's a VCR? What's a mall?
And you decide I am not going to drive my Saturn over to the mall to get my free VCR.
I'm just going to sit at home. You cannot then like wait six months and say, yeah, that guy lied to me when he told me I want a free VCR.
I never got the VCR.
Right? I know you can all relate. Everyone listening can relate regardless of their age
Especially to owning a Saturn
Yes
Right and so the same thing
Right, so your is your light who didn't receive his land thing can't sit there and say oh God told me he was gonna give me this land, but he didn't
Yeah, they have to go take it. Yeah, he did you just didn't go take it go take it
Right? He told you go here.
and you will get it and you didn't go there.
So you didn't get it, right?
So then, right?
As we said, that's pre-Tora.
Right? That's not with reference to the Torah.
So the Torah, the way the Torah relates to the land
is after that fact.
The life that they will have in the land
or not have in the land is gonna be based on
faithfulness to the commandments of the Torah.
And that's why when you get to the end of the book of Deuteronomy
and you get to the blessings in the curses,
the blessings of the curses are not about going to heaven
or going to hell.
There's nothing in the Torah that says
if you keep the Torah perfectly, you go to heaven.
Right?
Yep.
Or achieve salvation.
Yeah.
Or anything like that.
It says if you keep the Torah perfectly,
You will have a long and healthy and-
prosperous life in the land.
And if not, you're going to end up dead or in exile.
And we all know which of those two Israel corporately chose,
right? Historically, because we've read the rest of the Old Testament.
But so as we said, this is the lowest level.
Right?
This is the lowest level is dealing with the land and life and the land.
Now, even this lowest level of the Torah, remember the land functions as a sign, right?
It's an icon.
Okay, it is an image.
So it's not just this, right?
It points to more than this, but it is pointing, right?
It is pointing.
Part of what it's pointing to is a pattern.
It's a pattern we all already not only read about in Genesis, but talked about tonight.
That is the pattern of Adam being formed,
the way Israel was formed,
Adam being placed in the garden,
Israel being brought into the land,
Adam being unfaithful and being expelled from paradise,
Israel being unfaithful and being expelled
from the land into exile.
It's a pattern that repeats.
And so it points, the land points to bigger things
But at a very base level there is this sort of land level.
What's the next level up?
And the next level up is the way the Torah interacts with sin.
So now we've moved from something that's at the level of icons,
something that's at the level of sign to...
Okay, now we're talking about sin, now we're talking about this obstacle.
on the path of salvation. Okay. And how the Torah relates to that. The Torah does not
and does not claim to solve the problem of sin. It doesn't solve it. In fact, it can't solve
it. New Testament, St. Paul, and everybody else in New Testament is going to make this point.
the Torah can't, doesn't solve this problem, doesn't pr-
promised to solve this problem. But it does certain things in managing this problem.
Okay. And so there's sort of three ways that we're going to talk about that the Torah
aids with this in problem. Oh, we just got to say we just got a really
relevant question in the YouTube chat, which directly connects what you're saying. So
the question is, what I'd like to know.
is why the Torah is so complicated in its commandments compared to what Adam was given.
So I think what you're about to say kind of answers this. Yes. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
So sin in the world, right, certainly complicates things.
Right. Death in the world certainly complicates things.
right Adam did not have to do
mortality. He did not have to deal with sin. He did not have to deal with the effects of sin
on himself and on his own, a meaning like weakness. Right. And he did not have the demonic powers
corrupting him. When when one showed up to corrupt him, it happened real fast. But that's um
He did not have face.
demonic influence the way we do. Right. And so as I was just saying, yeah, the Torah
was going to address this, but the Torah isn't going to solve this. The three ways,
right, that we're going to talk about that the Torah interacts with sin. First of all,
the Torah brings the knowledge of sin. St. Paul talks about this extensively, like in Romans.
So
The Torah doesn't invent sin.
Yeah, sin has an existential reality to it.
You know, it's actually destructive to you whether anyone told you not to do that or not. Right, right. So there are some people who take this view that
the
Something is a sin because God said not to do it
Right.
We just got a weird nominalist view, but there's, right, it's not essentially a saying,
God just said not to do it, and so now it's a sin, right?
So there being, being a commandment makes it a sin, right?
And that is the exact opposite of the truth, right?
And I can give you a perfect example from the Torah itself, okay?
Is anyone want to argue with me based on the stories of say Jacob and Leah and Rachel
that polygamy was not a problem before the Torah?
Did not go well.
Right.
You say adultery was not a problem before.
The Ten Commandments.
Lying was cool. No, yeah, bearing false winners was totally cool, but they've got had to say no stop
Everybody's like oh man. I love bearing false witness
Yeah, that's
That's not a thing right the Torah brings the knowledge of sin
Right now you you know what is sin and what is not it's like warning labels right
knows could be helpful if you pay attention to them.
Those can save your life if you pay attention to them.
Right? And now St. Paul points out that even in this case, they sometimes have a perverse counter
effect. Right? I don't know if women have had this experience. But as someone who was once a
teenage boy, the quickest way to get me to try to do something was to tell me that I'm not allowed
to it was dangerous or I-
shouldn't do it. That was sort of the quickest way to get me to do it. And St. Paul talks about how
he himself and his own experience, right? How he hadn't even thought about coveting until he read
thou shalt not come right to your eat. Yeah. Yeah. You're not allowed to do this. And it's like,
right? It's just like when you're when you're in confession, you know, if you're a priest, like don't
Don't give the person any ideas.
Yeah.
Don't mention sins that they haven't heard of before.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah. Well, yeah, you have to limit your questions, right? Right, right.
Right. Right. Like you may want to ask, you mean consecutively or simultaneously, but
it's not always good to ask. Right. Right. Um, the, uh, so, right. So towards an event by
the Torah lays out here is what is sin. Here is what is dangerous. Here is what is deadly
in the world, right? Here's what to avoid. The Torah also...
provides a means of directly managing sin.
Not dealing with it once overall, because you have to keep doing it, right?
You have to keep doing the sin offerings every day.
You have to keep doing the day of atonement every year, right?
But there is this sort of management system, right?
To manage sin, confession, repentance, right?
That is built in there.
And the Torah also has provisions.
that are intended to help us understand the sin.
Right? A lot and and what I'm referring to under this heading is a lot of the commandments in the Torah that have to do with uncleanness, like we've talked about before, unclean is not the same thing as sin.
Okay, it's not a sin to go to the bathroom.
Right. Okay.
The, but it leaves you unclean.
Bye!
The rules for clean and unclean not only are many of them good as community health regulations right at a very literal level, but
also
The way mildew is handled
Right the way people with contagious skin disorders are handled
These give images of what sin is like how it infects how it spreads if not dealt with properly
However, it requires cleansing and purification.
How that cleansing and purification have to be to-
You can't leave a little, or it will come back.
All of these things are meant to educate about sin and how it works.
To aid people in avoiding sin, to aid people in repentance.
But none of those commandments actually touch on sin's existence.
Yeah, ending it once and for all.
or its ability to get its hands on somebody if they yield to it.
Right. But that is a deeper level than the land stuff. Right. But then and very importantly,
and often lost sight of, right, unfortunately, is the upper tier, the actual purpose of
the Torah which is about surprise surprise if you've been tracking with us.
far this episode about imaging God, about being formed in the likeness of God. And it's not
just me saying this is the highest part of the Torah. Christ says so. Yes, in Matthew 23, 23,
where he says, woe to you scribes and Pharisees hypocrites, for your tith, mint and Dylan,
and have neglected the wadier matters of the law.
and mercy and faithfulness. These you ought to have done without neglecting the others.
So what is weightier? I mean, just to be more serious? No. No, it's, I mean, I think that's
the most people read it is. It just means that the serious part. Well, I do have to note,
by the way, that woe to you scribes and Pharisees is literally cursing them. Yeah. So sorry, Trent Horn.
But uh...
So, notice, right, the weightier matters, justice, mercy, faithfulness, right?
These are the weightier matters.
So the word that means weighty or heavy in Hebrew is Kavod.
Kovod is also often translated as glory as in God.
But also often, right, to separate it from the word you've probably heard in terms of what the Hebrew word is for God's glory is Shikina, right?
Shikina.
Yeah, that's how I heard it when I was growing up.
Shikina is God's glory is in like the manifestation, the glory cloud, right?
The fiery cloud that we
see manifests itself. Havode is the word that Moses uses when he sitels God he wants to see his
Havode. Right. Sometimes translate English that he wants to see his glory. When he's told, you can't
see me and live. Yeah. Right. Which by the way, remember, is nine verses after it says that Moses
spoke to him face to face. Right, right, right. And so this.
idea of weight of heaviness is far closer to the later concept of essence or being.
Right. So what Christ is saying here is that justice and mercy and faithfulness are the core
of the Torah, the essence of the Torah. Yeah. And these other things like tithing from your
Erb Garden. Right? Our
peripheral, right? Now he doesn't say they're unimportant or dumb or don't worry about them.
Yeah, he says do those things, but yeah, without neglecting the core, right? Yeah, right. And also,
by the way, right? Well, we continue that. So we have this mistaken idea that we've talked about
about this other show before the sort of translation chain that gets us
from the word Torah to the word law in English, but because we're so used to referring to it
as the law and seeing it translated as law, we immediately think about it in legalistic
terms, shocking, I know. That's something called the law would be thought of in a legalistic
way, right? But that's not at all the way it was thought about by anyone in the first
century. That's not the way Christ talks about it. Right? Christ, of course, says what
about the greatest commandment. Love the Lord your God with all your heart, soul, mind,
and strength. Right? The second is like it left your neighbor as yourself. Right? In
these is summed up. All the Torah and the prophets, not just the whole Torah is summed up
in it, but the whole Hebrew Bible, the whole scriptures are summed up in those two commandments.
Right? Meaning if you're, if you do those, you're doing everything else that's required
of you.
And St. Paul says the same thing in Romans. He says the one who loves keeps the whole Torah.
Yeah. Yeah. And it's not just Christ and St. Paul. Christ and St. Paul are certainly enough.
Yeah. I mean, I mean, this, well, this also reminds me of a similar kind of saying, which I think it was our patricistic professor passed on.
on at least he said it to my class,
I think you had the same professor
I did, Dr. Venumine.
He said he didn't pass on. That's not what you were saying. He passed on this saying. He passed on this saying, which he passed on. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. He is still living. May God granted him.
And nobody but freaking out. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. No. But I mean, I remember him saying.
You know, seminarians believe it or not, everybody have endless conversations about things that you don't need to have endless conversations about. And one of them is fasting.
And he, which seems to be a particular obsession with American Orthodox Christians, but
I mean, fasting is very important, but endless conversations about it are not usually.
But I remember him saying that there was – he was in a situation where I think he was
a fasting day, but he was visiting a friend who took him to a restaurant and then he realized
there was really nothing at the restaurant that was fast-friendly.
And then the person said to him, I think he was in Greece, in Greek, a saying which I don't
know what it sounds like in Greek, but the seeing was essentially that love.
It also obviates the necessity of the fast.
You know, that the hospitality and the love that was being shown
is greater than the gain that can be had from the ascetical action of fasting for a particular meal.
So it shows the same kind of principle.
You know, that love is the fulfillment of the whole love God.
It doesn't mean you know, hey, I love you, I can do.
Whatever I want, you know, no, no, no, that's not the that's not the point at all.
But that the genuine Christian love is doing it.
It's doing what God wants.
You will do all those other things if you are truly loving God with all your heart.
So my straight end, right?
Yeah.
That's why St. Paul, right?
He gives the fruit of the spirit.
He says against such things there is no law.
Right?
Yeah.
So yeah.
So it's not just Christ and Saint Paul.
Who who held to this right this is I mean they would certainly be enough right but they were not like
This is not revisionism right what Christ says those two sum up the law of the prophets all the teachers of the law around them
Right all the Torah teachers all the Pharisees and stuff are like you have spoken well right like they all acknowledge right like yes
That is true. That's why you'd Matthew 23 23 that we just heard
Christ calls them hypocrites
Right.
Because they know and would agree that the core the center the important things like justice and mercy and faithfulness are the core of the Torah
They know that they just don't act like it
There's no live like it thus making them hypocrites right so this isn't some novel
Christ comes along St. Paul or St. Paul comes along and turns the whole Torah on its head
Right.
No, this is the way everyone read it.
This is what it's set because this is what it's teaching.
Yeah.
So that is the deepest and most important level, right, is manifest, a justice, mercy,
faithfulness.
What are these?
These are what we, the other extra, which we're called divine energies.
These are God's activity in the world.
So the core of the tour of the tour is really...
about is setting forth a way of life that leads to being formed in the image of the perfect
man, being formed into the likeness of God, which are the same thing.
That's ultimately what it's aimed at.
That's complicated by the fact that we also have to manage sin and these other issues that
have intervened, but the core of it is still the same.
same idea of salvation. So then what is what is salvation for an Israelite and how did they receive it?
Right? Well, like we just said, it meant they were faithful in following the way of life that God had
said out before them in the Torah. Right? But what does it mean? Right? To keep Torah?
This is the same
question that everybody was asking. This is this is the essential question that was asked to Christ when he gave the response
Right of the the greatest commandments, right? This is what all of these questions and discussions in Jewish circles in the first century AD
were about
What does it mean to keep Torah? They all understood that this is what we need to do, but what does it really mean?
Yeah, right and they all because they all knew
it couldn't and didn't
Just mean like okay, I follow this list of rules
Legalistically mechanically right
They all knew that wasn't it
Right and so what are we saying we're saying that
The core of the Torah and the way they found salvation was by pursuing man's original purpose
Becoming like God right following these core things of the way of life
Right, putting the world in order.
filling it with life, right? And these other elements of the Torah, these lower levels, right, of
having land to live on and raise your family on and having a means of dealing with sin, those are
there to facilitate the core pursuit of salvation. Yeah, right. To make that possible. And part of what
accentuates this? Is when we ask the question
So, we just asked that question, what does it mean for an Israelite?
Whether they're an Israelite in the undivided kingdom, whether they're an Israelite in the
northern kingdom of Judahite and the southern kingdom of Judahite and exile, a Judean
after the exile, right?
With keeping Torah.
But if we go during that same time period, and we say, what is salvation for a non-Israelite?
And how does the non-Israelite receive it?
Because they haven't been given the Torah.
Yeah, they don't have all this teaching about how to be faithful to God.
Right?
They don't have this way of living set out in detail before them in the Torah, right?
Which, and this is why St. Paul in Romans 2 is saying, like, even though he's talking
about Gentiles, you're right, he says, well, you're just saying the Torah is no big deal.
He's like, no, it's a big deal.
We have...
all of this given to us, right? That they did not, right? But salvation was still possible for
them because we see people, name and, right? All the guys over here, all through the Old Testament,
who are not Israelites, who don't become Israelites, right? Like Ruth becomes an Israelite,
even though she's a Moabite. Name and doesn't become an Israelite, right? Their Plutty, who don't become
Israelites and yet become followers of the God of Israel.
pursue salvation. Right? So for example, they don't have this whole means of
managing and dealing with sin. Yeah. So what's going on with their sin? Right? Now
there's certain sin that we find talked about in the story of Noah, things that
are addressed to everyone, not just Israelites, like not committing murder. Right?
Bye.
not doing human sacrifices to your pagan gods.
Right?
There are certain things that even a non-Jet op-dose are sin.
But most of this stuff, right?
They don't know.
Well, what we're told by the New Testament,
I know this might be a freak out moment for some people.
But what St. Paul explicitly says in both Acts 17
and Romans 1 is that during this whole period
before the coming of
Christ. God overlooked the sins of the Gentiles. Yeah. I mean, it's what it says. Now I know some of you folks out there think that's not possible. Yes, God must punish sin. Yes, God is not able to overlook sin. Right. Yeah.
uh
But right that's what we're told
Right but we're told it in the contact stuff right
Because they were not given the Torah, God was patient with them.
And God had a lower standard with them.
But for example, that's why in Romans 1, say Paul says,
now the wrath of God is being revealed against the sin of the nations
and talks about all the sins the nations are committing.
Now that the gospel is going out to them,
now they're called to repent.
Now the
gift that was only given to Israel is being given through Israel to the whole world, now
they have to repent. In previous days, they could plead ignorance. Right? Now they can.
Right? And this interestingly, this idea that Gentiles, that non-Jews have this kind
of leeway in terms of...
of sin is still a belief of orthodox Judaism. So after some extended discussions, for example,
I have had orthodox Jewish people tell me after I explain right the orthodox doctrine of
the trinity to them, they say, well, from a Jewish perspective, they still think it's
They're not signing on for the doctor of the trinity.
But...
They'll tell me that they think it's within the amount of idolatry that's allowed to Gentiles
Wow
Now that makes the people's heads explode right like wait what
They believe Gentiles are allowed a certain amount of idolatry well, yes, because they weren't given the Torah
So orthodox Jews still believe this is the case. There's a lot of things.
and the commandments, right, you've heard us talk on the show before about
Acts 15 being a very literal interpretation of Leviticus and that the vast majority
of the commandments of the Torah were never seen to apply to Gentiles, but
Orthodox Judaism takes that farther. Today, they say Gentiles are forbidden to keep
So they would say Gentiles are forbidden to keep the Sabbath.
I mean, right.
Check.
Yeah.
He brought it to people.
Sabotary.
All your dispensationalists and trades to.
Adventists.
Yeah.
Dispensationalists and trades Jews.
You need to get to know some actual Jews.
Yeah.
Because you're going to find out they don't believe in practice.
you think they do.
So, yeah, so they still have that leeway and that's juxtaposed against what St. Paul says in like Romans 1.
From the Christian perspective, because Gentiles are now included in the church, which is Israel, because they're now included now they're held to the high standard.
Yeah.
To the high standard of the call.
of the Torah, right, that we were talking about of the highest level of the Torah.
And so, but so if we're talking about before the birth of Christ Gentiles,
they found salvation, and St. Paul talks about this in Romans 2, they found salvation by keeping the
righteous requirements of the Torah on them even though they didn't have it.
Yeah. So they functioned as a Torah for themselves as St. Paul says. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Right. And what was that?
That was imaging God in their world. Being merciful, being just
the way here matters of the law in their dealings. Right. Um, these kind of things. Right. And
and pursuing God.
But what that makes abundantly clear.
Right? So when St Paul comes and says, the works of the Torah, meaning the particular commandments
given to the Jewish people were never about salvation, right? That becomes obvious once we think about this.
Because yes, everyone from all the other nations who found salvation found it without them.
Right that that wasn't right and that's why St. Paul goes back to Abraham
Hmm pre Torah
Right pre Torah
It talks about how Abraham found salvation
Right and points out that
You cannot that the mistake the judisers were making is that
that they were treating.
the Torah commandments as sort of a re-negotiation of terms of the covenant with Abraham.
Right? Meaning all of these other provisos were being put on the promise about becoming like the
stars of heaven. Now you've got to be circumcised to become like the stars of heaven.
And say Paul is saying no. He's got a two-pronged attack number one.
He points to Abraham in Genesis 15 because he hasn't been circumcised yet.
And number two, he points to non-Jews, finding salvation.
Before their inclusion.
Yeah, albeit sporadically.
All right, well, that wraps up the second half of this episode of Laura Spirits.
We'll be right back with the third half, see you soon.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung
We'll be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Written by Father Pavel Sochek of Blessed Memory with wisdom and a deep love for
God, the essentials in Orthodox Christian cataclysm is a book for all who
hunger to understand what
what it means to live as an Orthodox Christian.
From an explanation of the creed to an exploration of the sacraments
and the role of Holy Scripture and tradition,
this slim volume contains everything the new convert needs
to participate fully in the church
and to grow and faith as an Orthodox Christian.
Find it today at store.ancientfaith.com.
That's store.ancientfaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
with Father Andrew Stephen Damick.
father Steven DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
And we're back. Hope everybody's enjoying this episode. We're just a couple weeks out
from Holy Week. I should mention by the way, we will have an episode releasing on Thursday
not of Holy Week, but we will be in
sure. So it will be a pre-recorded
episode. But
And nonetheless, you will have something for your listening pleasure from either, if
you're on the west coast to listen to you before you go to church or find the east coast.
I don't know, you could stay up late as father Steven, I guess, after one of the biggest
one of the biggest services of Holy Week, the passion, 12 passions, gospel's mans.
But yeah, we'll be there.
Well, I'm hoping that unlike certain years, I won't be up at two in the morning passing
a kidney stone on that.
Thank you for that memory.
You weren't there. I was a dare but I remember you describing it to me. Yes.
Where were you by hour of greatest lead father Andrew? Well, apparently according to someone in I don't know if I sent you the meme that was created for this but
according to someone in our Lord of Spirits group there's people literally dreaming me into their homes. So maybe you could have done that. I don't know.
What's the name of that movie?
There's this Nicholas Cage movie that came out last year.
Yes, I didn't where he starts appearing in people's dreams.
Yeah, yeah.
Well, and like a professor, it's actually a really interesting movie.
Really?
Even though it's got Nicholas Cage.
No, it is, it is, it's interesting because yeah,
like he's this college professor and like he starts,
students are saying he's appearing in their dreams
and he's doing these like nice reassuring things.
so he becomes the sort of weird-
celebrity, but then they start having dreams where he's doing like horrible things.
Oh.
And like people turn on him and he's like, I didn't do anything.
Like I'm.
Well, yeah, apparently.
So what's kind of funny though is, so one of the means it was made because of this,
I had nothing to do with this.
Zero.
Nothing to do with this.
It's you think it does protest too much.
Now, well, so there's, there's this, supposedly a bunch of people over the world have dreams
about some guy.
and they draw pictures of him and all the pictures look alike, you know.
And so there's a website, thisman.org.
Have you dreamed this man?
And you can go to that website and you can submit your photos or not photos.
But your drawings and describe your experiences and so forth.
It's not me.
I mean, it doesn't, it's not me.
I swear.
But maybe it's starting out there in Kansas now because that's where the dreamer apparently was.
So I don't know you never know I could be in your home through your
dreams father Steve, that's all I'm saying. I'm not doing it. You know, I'm just loving
my life. I'm trying to think I don't think I've ever had a dream with you in it. I don't
remember having one with you in it either. So, you know, I don't usually dream of ogres.
Okay, so we do actually have a couple of callers and one is another John from Missouri.
Now, if it's not the same John, do we know it's the same Missouri?
So John.
in whichever Missouri you're in,
is it the same Missouri?
What form of Missouri looks at?
I'm feeling kind of like Cooper looking at it
as doppelganger.
You know, Missouri is where the Church of Jesus Christ
of Latter-day Saints say that the second coming
is gonna happen in Independence, Missouri.
Did you know that?
And that religious organization
have bought a whole bunch of land
around Independence, Missouri
for the mustering of the Saints.
know that father I actually live in the northwest corner it's almost not necessary.
Like an Nebraska put together. Oh, what do you get when you put Iowa and Nebraska
together? Apparently you. Oh, no. All right. What is on your mind? Well, father Andrew,
I wanted to ask perhaps a warm up question for you, especially since you're an expert on
rings.
one ring in particular. What was the actual function of the green ring from the black lodge?
The green ring from the black lodge
Maybe father Steve and I would just make something up
But I'm just I actually know the answer so yeah, I'm sure you do go ahead
It protected you from lodge spirits possessing
I think it seemed really weird, but I couldn't
I put my finger on whether or not it helped you, or if it took you into the lodge and made things worse for you.
Not sure.
No, if you obviously, in one of the missing pieces, they take the ring off Annie.
I do remember that, but there's also the with this ring, Ivy Wed, so I don't know.
Yeah.
I see now this is a twin peaks thing.
Yes it is.
Yeah I've never
I watched, I think I watched eight minutes of the first episode and I was like, I,
you don't like creepy.
So again, I don't like creepy.
What can I say?
It's the same reason I watched eight minutes of Stranger Things.
But I did watch several episodes of Dr. Who.
But then you asked about the green rings in the Magicians Nephew.
I mean, I could tell you all about that, but.
Oh, that's the S. Lewis.
I don't know anything about that.
I know, I know.
Well, you at least know how about the power rings used by, uh,
TNT and Dan the dynamite.
That's probably out of my lead too.
Yeah, I went away and that breaks on child.
I could have just done a green lantern thing, but no, no, I had to go for like
quality comics of the 1940s.
Well, fathers, I had a question about a topic that I think is almost addressed
before on the podcast, especially when we were dipping into conversations about
hell.
I'm considering going back to Tahos to finish my first masters potentially, and I was trying to think of different topics.
And this one thing that keeps recurring to me is something that I've
Saw a long time ago. I became worth it in action 2011 and one of my
with the doctor mentors who felt like he was too old to be my godfather shared the river of
fire theology with me and the what do you want to call it the script or the written portion of
that original talk and I was very surprised and bothered by it. I was former Protestant but since
being Orthodox now for over a decade I've seen lots of things from the Holy Fathers that talk about
hell almost
material, but I can tell, especially you would say John Persostom or even St. Ignatius
Ranchaninov that they have room for nuance even if they're being very direct in their
descriptions, and they're very careful to not say that it's a material fire.
But then every, there's two categories of Orthodox books on death primarily that I've seen,
spous what I would call same-placism theology and ones that don't talk about hell at all because
they're focused more on the transition during death and the potential meaning of toll houses.
And then I found maybe two words of ox bokeh that very briefly mentioned hell as being a quote-unquote
place. And of course, I think there's room for nuance with what place means with that as well.
But I think an issue is that I
I feel like River Fire and the same place,
like hell is the same,
or hell is God's love of experience to differently.
But this kind of implication of a sort of semi,
let's say it was say right,
apacatastasis.
Apacatastasis.
It's apacatastasis.
Where everybody goes to heaven,
they just some people experience it as hell
and that this is somehow more loving
then brought us in a Roman Catholic.
like formulations of what hell is.
And I've heard it in two homilies,
and the lead up was always about as long as my lead up
that I've had now.
And it usually starts with a subject
that has nothing to do with hell.
And it ends up with orthodoxy is more merciful
because our doctrine of hell is that hell is in a place
that God's love.
And of course, the quotes that they use
are quotes taken completely out of context
from the fathers.
And they're really favorite father
for this, the St. Isaac the Syrian.
And the literal quote that the U of T ends with,
hell.
the primary torment of hell will be regret, which is not an experience of God's love,
but an experienced person.
So, anyway, I was wondering if we could get kind of like at least from your two perspectives
and experience a more definitive perspective on how to calibrate this,
because I just, I feel like there's got to be plenty of maybe untranslated.
material from the fathers about death and hell and like what but that they're not translated
because it's not interesting or because it's scary or it doesn't seem like it's about
salvation but if it's a kind of a pocket of stasis then it's actually a kind of salvation
it's just a self-funded death and then of course the other question is where are our
body that's great but if we
We have bodies.
Are we, is it semi-originism where we have bodies,
but we're floating around the orb
and we just experience God differently?
Or are we in a location?
And how does that correspond to actually the work
that you were talking about earlier
with mankind's salvation is primarily lived out
through working and what eternal life would be?
Wow.
Okay.
Yeah, I remember.
I remember when I was first becoming Orthodox now almost 30 years ago that that article,
the River of Fire by Alexander Kalamero's, was a big hit that it really got circulated
around. And honestly, back in the late 1990s, when there wasn't a lot about Orthodox Christianity
on the internet, that was one of the early pieces that was on back then. And so my sense
is that it's had a kind of outsized effect on English speaking Orthodox Christianity
because of its availability from...
that sort of early point and not early in the sense of orthodoxy in America but early
in the sense of orthodoxy becoming more accessible to people because of the internet.
So here's my opinions about that article.
Well, first I'll say that actually there was some rather interesting and lengthy critiques
of it that went around which unfortunately are not on the internet.
more because they were very fascinating to read. But I, there's something about it that
I think is true, like the sense that our God is consuming fire, right, death by holiness,
that kind of stuff, which of course we've talked about many times on this show, the idea
that being in the presence of God in an unrepentant manner is harmful to you.
So that's totally a thing.
But my problem with the picture,
and I'm pretty sure that you can still read this article on the internet.
I'm still out there.
My problem with that picture is that it fundamentally presents
one's eternal destiny,
which we can shorthand call Heaven or Hell.
Bliss, salvation and the kingdom of God, or damnation,
with all of
that entails. My problem with it is that it fundamentally depicts God as passive. That
what you experience in the afterlife is God just pouring out the same thing on everybody
but it's up to you how are you going to experience it. So that's not completely wrong. It is
up to you what your experience of the life of the age to come is. But it's not that
God is this sort of passive divine being emanating whatever on everyone and you just either
have the receptors for it or you don't.
And the reason I don't like that is because it says explicitly in the gospels that
God sends people to one or the other destination.
They send them.
That God is actively making a judgment based on who that person is, based on what they
we have done.
but he's actively doing it. Right? And the other problem is that of course all
language about the life of the age to come, human language is going to tend to be
metaphorical in some way because we can't really encapsulate it. But the problem
with saying, well, it's not two different places. It's really one place. You're
literally correcting the language of the Bible when you do that. Now I'm not
saying that means we need to literalize and absolutize this sort of two-place.
language, but we shouldn't say it's not that because that language is in the Scriptures.
You know, enter into the kingdom or depart, I never knew you. That's that's location language.
Okay. That's in Matthew chapter 25, which of course we hear every year on the Sunday of the
last judgment and you know, we should know if we're going to know any part of the Bible,
you should definitely know the gospels. So I that's those are my problems with it article. I think
gets into
does some good things, but it also fundamentally
distorts scriptural language.
It denies scriptural language, which I'm used
to hearing that kind of thing from liberal,
mainline Protestants.
You know, they want to just write parts of the Bible off
that they don't like.
I'm used to that kind of thing.
But for Faithful Orthodox Christian to do that?
No, no, you can't do that.
Any theology that you're gonna give
about the life of the age to come
about anything Orthodox Christian.
It needs to take the scriptures into account and needs to take the scriptures as the basis
for what you're going to say.
It needs to take the scriptures as the core of what you're going to say.
This is the very center of our tradition as Orthodox Christians.
So if you're saying something and you're basically correcting the scriptures and you have a big
methodological problem, right?
So I mean, I think it's, like I said, I think it's some ways that article is useful and
some ways I don't think it is.
So I will now invite the um actually from my colleague in Louisiana.
Yeah, I don't like the articles much as you do.
I think it's the way worse the liberal Protestant is.
Liberal Protestants just say everybody goes to heaven or there isn't one.
Yeah, I like because they've heard imagined too many times.
Wasn't that the most inspiring song we heard during COVID though?
It is if you're a boomer lip. Yeah
So, yeah. And so the reason this is worse to me is like, just people can we stop and think
once in a while. Stop and think about it, okay. Is God not aware that his love is like
torturing these people eternally? Right. If he is aware that he loves them, why is he
torturing them eternally.
Like you're basically turning God into Lenny from of a Mice and Men.
Wow.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right?
Like, this is, I mean, it's as bad as what I would compare it to is the universalist goofballs
who try to do the purgatoryal health thing where they're like, oh no, like if someone
doesn't love God and doesn't want to be would
doesn't want to be with him, then he just like puts them in this torture chamber until
they do love him.
Yeah, he's going to beat them until he's like, oh yeah, that's way better.
Now, God is going close from fatal attraction.
Like, what?
Like, that's not better, dude.
Like, that's right.
Yeah, so there's that.
This whole idea of place, yes, while Andrew's...
like, first of all, every father is clear to the point of, if you deny it, you're not a Christian
about the bodily resurrection. Yes. Okay. Even our Roman Catholic friends with so much emphasis on
the beatific vision and so much cognitive dissonance about how that works with the bodily resurrection,
affirm the bodily resurrection, okay, despite the potential issues, okay.
You can't be a Christian and deny the bodily resurrection.
You don't work.
So we're not talking about heaven or hell
and then being one place or two places.
We're talking about, everything's gonna be resurrected.
We're talking about the life of the world to come.
The new heavens and the new earth,
the transfigured, renewed heavens and earth
and our transfigured resurrected bodies,
to which as we've been talking about on the show recently,
category
the space and time will not apply in the same way.
Yeah.
I mean, there's still material, there's still, but yeah.
And so we get, we get, when we talk here about the state of eternal condemnation, we get
metaphors in Scripture and in the fathers that don't work together.
If you have a fire that's eternally burning, how can it also be complete darkness?
Yeah
Right? We also get madness and the diminution of the human person and the demonization of the human right?
Like there are all these things and there's being shut outside, right?
As as Father Edger just quote a crisis, depart from me. How do you depart from someone who's omnipresent?
Right? Like you you literally can't take it literally.
It's impossible to take it literally.
So we're told enough to know this is bad, inconceivably bad.
Like literally we can't conceive of how horrible this fate is.
Right. And we're not able to understand what that will be like, because we, as we've said on the show recently,
right, in this life, in our mortal flesh, right, constrained as we are by categories of time and space,
of time in space. We can't imagine what it's like to not be so. Right? And so we can-
can only get analogies and imagery and this kind of thing to communicate to us.
But those images were given communicate very evocatively that this is something that we
want to avoid at all costs.
It is indeed a major bummer.
That's what we call a call back in the biz.
Right.
Yeah.
So that's what that's about.
I think a lot of the discussion you're reading is,
people need to sit and think about it a little more.
It's, it's, it's, you're taking,
people are taking images and ideas very literally
and running with them in odd directions.
And the directions they're running with those images
actually kind of evade the point of the image
in the first place.
Right? Like the purpose of the...
imagery of the river of fire in Daniel and the lake of fire in St. Matthew's gospel and
Revelation is not to soften our idea of God's judgment.
So if you run with that imagery in a way that is deliberately intended to try to soften
someone's view of God's judgment, right?
like deliberately it seems breaking something right and miss
misleading people. So we should stop doing it. That's well, I have held from the
U's net days that the white lodge and the black lodge are the same place. And that's why
there's checkered board flooring. Oh, you mentioned checkered board flooring. Now all
the that's what I have to say about that. The Freemason freakouts will be honest. All
right. So you got a couple of good rants there, John. What do you think?
I mean, I guess I have like a couple of short questions.
the speed back because obviously I have a lot more that could be said on it, right? That's not worth a brief phone call.
And we don't have two more hours to push this into the first five-hour episode talking about Twin Peaks and how it relates to...
No, we don't. Atonement.
No, we do not.
I would love to.
That could be a separate podcast. I think Fathers would even should do his own independent Twin Peaks commentary podcast.
with what you should be posted.
No, we will not.
But that's why I said independent, with a little bit of professional wrestling thrown in as well.
I can tie it in like you did with Tolkien.
Father Steven, so do you think this would be worth a thesis in some kind of way of working out the details on the scriptural,
and the patricistic tradition and expanding it possibly into a more holistic direction.
Yeah, I think I think and even even framing it as a response to
River of fire might be a good way to frame such a thesis
Yeah
I was thinking of calling it hell isn't good
Yeah, yeah, yeah
Why you shouldn't love hell
Why God doesn't love hell and neither should you heaven isn't going to hurt
Although you should definitely check out Father Stevens article.
unfortunately, yes, on the orthodoxy and heterodoxy web blog.
I would definitely have to check that out.
Yes.
So Father Mike also,
the Greek, the Greek word,
heaven isn't too far away.
Keep that in mind.
Is.
Baby, do you know it?
That's worth.
Sorry.
Go ahead, John.
Go ahead, go ahead.
No, no, no.
So Father Steven, on the brief, because you mentioned that you
disagree with Jay Dyer on Twin Peaks.
And I think I might as well.
What?
What's the gist of the meaning of the show?
And does it change if you watch,
not just season one and two,
but also firewalk with me?
And then does it change if you watch season three?
I don't think it changes.
I think you get sort of a purified refined form
of it in the later stuff.
And I think there's
a whole bunch of themes. So too much too much to talk about right now.
Thank you for entertaining me, Father.
I'm not sure how much I disagree with Jake is Jay is evasive and running from debate on the topic.
So yeah, I'll just throw that in there at the end.
All right, all right. Well, thank you for calling, John. We'll take one more call. We have Jim,
Jim Jim Jim calling from St. Augustine, Florida. I was a
remind myself not to say Saint Augustine. I know it's Augustine down there. I've been there.
So Jim, welcome to the Lord's Spirit's podcast. Jim, I have a question first. Do you often
turn toward a camera? No one else can see and make facial expressions?
I do not. Okay. You're not that Jim then. That's why. Different Jim.
Okay.
I know, Paul, I don't get the reference, but...
Okay, just join the club.
You and I will be over here together.
So what's on your mind, Jim?
Well, my kids love singing in the rain.
And the first two times that they watched it,
I thought that Donald O'Connor was Danny Kay.
So I didn't know if Danny Kay does a rendition
of Moses deposes his throne.
do the roses or did Father Stephen have the same take that I did on singing in the
rain.
All right.
No, he did it also.
He did it.
That's an old bit.
That's an old vaudeville bit.
Yeah.
A lot of covers back in those days.
Actually, you can find it on YouTube.
You can get Danny K doing this particular tongue twister in 1951 on YouTube.
So he predated thing into the rain.
He was the OG.
Well, now it was before.
It's like it's probably I a good
fall slowly.
I turned step by step in Shpai
inch.
Anyway.
All right.
And no, well, that was a nice
easy question.
Thank you very much, Jim.
Lovely town you have there.
You have everybody should know
by the way, Saint Augustine has
an actual like late Renaissance
era fort.
I think it's the only one in North America.
Definitely a nice old fort.
Built by the Spanish.
So definitely worth checking out.
All right, third half of this episode.
Head on into the New Testament, yeah.
I suppose.
I like the Danny K is now on topic on this show.
I mean, who doesn't like Danny K?
Just at all times.
Right.
I loved him in white Christmas.
He was...
lot of fun and yeah anyway completely non-controversial movie.
Okay, sorry. So yes, so now the new testament. So we find, as you might have seen coming,
long time, listeners, we find the
fulfillment of these things we've been talking about on our way from Genesis through the Old Testament in the New Testament.
And so, for example, not just in terms of the actual literal setting out of this idea by St. Paul in Romans 5, but in the New Testament we see Christ presented as the second Adam.
in that Christ is the perfect image of God, right?
He images the Father perfectly.
This is, I mean, this is all over the New Testament,
but think in, say, St. John's Gospel, right?
The words he says are the Father's words.
The things he does are the Father's deeds, right?
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I must be about my Father's business.
If you've seen me, you've seen the Father, right?
Yeah, and then of course.
St. Paul and Hebrews, right, he's the express image of his hypostasis, right, of the Father.
And not only that, not only is he the perfect image of God, but through him, the world,
the creation is finding and will find its ultimate transformation, right, into paradise.
So he.
succeeds right where Adam failed. But that's the Tellos, right? But if we go back to
the beginning and again, I'm sure saw this coming, dear listener, that the mystery,
which was hidden from everlasting and unknown of the angels, as it were, is
is revealed in Christ. Why is it?
that humanity and only humanity is able to be formed in this way into the likeness of God.
Right?
How is that?
How is the measure and the form of the perfect man also the perfect likeness of God?
and it's because of the perfect union of God and man of the divine nature and our
in the person of Jesus Christ, right?
And so the incarnation is the basis of theosis
and was the basis of theosis for Adam, right?
This is what's being gotten at by.
You will occasionally hear people say that
I may even have even phrased it this way in the past.
In fact, I probably have at least at some point
that the church was...
will say that even if Adam had not fallen had not been expelled from paradise, Christ would have been
incarnate. And I mean, that conveys the idea, but is not quite the idea in the sense that what
they're really getting at is this is that the basis of theosis being the purpose for which Adam
was created and the commandment he was given as St. Basil the Great said was the incarnation.
So the incarnation is presupposed by the creation of Adam.
This is what they're getting at.
That it is not an instance of fall or exposure for paradise,
therefore incarnation.
Right.
Because his creation presupposed it.
We also
Christ presented in the New Testament as the New Israel. We talked about how Israel
corporately had this kind of recapitulation or was another corporate enceiation of the
pattern that we saw with Adam being created brought into the land etc. Christ actually
recapitulates that accomplishes the goal.
that Israel was created for and failed that. Right? Because as Christ affirms, salvation
is from the Jews. Right? The idea was not that Israel was the chosen people. They were
quote unquote saved. All the other nations were damned or just not saved or whatever.
is that God was saving the world through Israel the way he saved.
the world through Noah. He's saving the world through Israel. And the way that was to happen
was by Israel keeping Torah by being different than all the other nations of the world. They
would draw the other nations of the world to come and worship the God of Israel. They would
draw them to return to God, having been scattered at Bable, draw them to return to the true God
who had created them right and Israel.
fails at that because Israel is unfaithful, Christ as faithful, accomplishes this and ends up
drawing all the nations back to their Creator. So Christ is the basis for the
This is 4 Salvation from Adam.
right for the core of salvation. Christ is the one who overcomes the separation
between Jew and Gentile, between Israel and the nations, right? Who overcomes
the the scattering of the nations, right? Christ also deals with the obstacles
that come about because of Adam's sin. Christ deals with...
sin, how, by removing it and by purifying us the world, right, from it. Think flood
again, right, that we talked about in the first half, right, removes sin purifies from sin.
So with sin removed, right, with Christ having dealt with sin. So we no longer need the repetitive
management because Christ is
dealt with it, that means death has served its purpose. Death having served its purpose,
Christ takes that power back from the devil, as Hebrews says. Right? The one who had held
the power of death was the devil, Christ defeats him, and Christ therefore becomes the judge
of the living and the dead.
No one else has any claim on humanity.
I do.
And if I...
Christ defeats the powers by disarming them. This is the language St. Paul uses. He disarms
the powers of principalities. How does he disarm them? Their weapon was death. Their weapon was
temptation of sin which leads to death. Having dealt with those, they are now disarmed. They are now
unable to afflict the saints.
Christ having done all of these things, Christ having done all of these things, what is,
what is salvation?
What is salvation for us now, for everyone now, right?
Salvation is, right?
Those obstacles being removed, being freed from sin and death by what Christ has done,
And then that being accomplished.
Revelation is what it always was.
From the creation of Adam,
S theosis is becoming like God,
and that's based not in what Christ has done,
but in who Christ is.
Hmm.
Right, who the person of Christ is.
That's what salvation is.
How is it received?
Right, how do any of us receive it?
Right, well, we receive it through the fulfillment of the Torah.
as we've talked.
about on the show before, the church is Israel. It is the restored Israel. Right? And so we
still have the Torah still in your Bible. It's right there at the beginning, right? But now,
right, it is received. It is practiced in a fulfilled way. Right? So for example, the sin
that was managed before is now done away with when we receive the
forgiveness of sin, the purification from sin, the cleansing from sin, that comes from Christ,
which we receive, first of all, in baptism, for the remission of sin, and then in ongoing forgiveness,
through confession, through repentance, through absolution. Right?
And so the sacraments now are the fulfillment of sacraments of the Church.
series are the fulfillment of the sacraments of the Torah. If you go back and listen to
the sacrament episodes, that's how every single one of them is structured. You start all
the old testament. Yep. Yeah. Right. And show how it takes on a fulfilled form, right, in
the new. Right. And so in the same way that a way of life grounded in commandments, three of them,
right was was set before Adam right and he was called to become like God through
faithfully following those commandments as a way of life right the same way a
way of life has been set before us and it's actually summed up by three
commandments.
Love the Lord your God with all your heart with all your-
with all your mind and with all your strength. Love your neighbor as yourself and repent.
Right, that summarizes the whole thing. Right, there's details, right? And there's a whole
detailed life of the church that like the other levels of the Torah facilitates us doing that.
Right, and powers us to do that.
Enables us.
to do that with the life of the church.
And so how do we receive salvation?
We receive salvation by faithfully following that way of life that's been set before us.
The person who's been forgiven, the person who's received the forgiveness of sins, the
person who's had terror of death taken away by Christ, the person who has been set free
Free.
from sin and from therefore from the demonic powers, that person stands in the same position as Adam did.
Meaning we are on a pathway that leads to infinity but toward Christ and becoming like him.
The full measure of the perfect man, which is Jesus Christ, and the likeness of God.
which is
or Jesus Christ
and that way of life is characterized by the fruit of the Spirit. You may notice that those things which Christ called the weight the heaviness the core of the Torah were fruit of the Spirit
because it just seems
St. Paul says in Romans, right? The Spirit writes the Torah in our hearts. The Spirit empowers us to keep its righteous requirements. Spirit empowers us
hours us.
to follow Christ, right? And that brings about our transformation into the likeness of Christ,
and that in turn transforms the world around us and allows us to become what humanity was created to be.
And so this is actually kind of summed up here in closing in Hebrews 6 verses
one and two. Yeah, which reads this way, therefore, let us leave the elementary doctrine of
Christ and go on to maturity, not laying again a foundation of repentance from dead works and
of faith toward God, and of instruction about washings, delaying on of hands, the resurrection
of the dead, and eternal judgment. Yeah, notice those things that St. Paul calls elementary
doctrines.
as this lower level, not the core, not the way to your part.
Yeah, this is the basics.
Yeah.
Are everything you will hear about in a lot of churches?
There is no beyond that.
Right.
Now, I'm talking about churches like buildings of worship, houses of worship, right?
Where do you go there?
that is all
you will hear about. Right? And what you will find is now I'm not saying there is no depth
to any tradition other than the Orthodox tradition. I am not saying that. But what you'll find is
every time one of those other traditions tries to go deeper, they're going to be groping around
in the dark toward a concept of theosis. Hmm. I mean, this is why so many, so many confessional
Protestants like Father Alexander.
Memmon. Yeah, they're going to be
growing around toward a concept of
theosis, whether it's it's called
deification, right, and even a lot of
the way the beatific vision has talked
about in Roman Catholicism, right, when
you start going deep, right, and when
a lot of the start going deep they
start going to Eastern fathers, even
ones who technically aren't saints in
Roman Catholicism.
This is why you dig deep into the Reformed tradition.
You start finding stuff about mystical union with Christ when you start digging into the
Lutheran tradition, more recently, like in the late 20th century, they just started using
the term Theosis.
Right?
Everywhere that's what you find.
Because and that's not a coincidence. That's not just them going like I don't know
I got nothing the orthodox come up with anything right it's because
What we've been trying to lay out to you tonight
Dear listener is real
It's in the Bible
From literally we started the first page of Genesis
Yeah, right. And if we wanted to, we could
quote and end up on the last page of Revelation.
Yeah.
That theosis, right?
This idea of us becoming conformed to the likeness, the perfect man, who is the perfect
likeness of God, right?
Our Lord Jesus Christ, that's it.
That's what salvation is.
It's the basis on which Man was created, the purpose for which he was created.
It's where we end up in the life of the world to come.
It's the core and the center and the weighty part of the Torah.
It's there all the way through.
It gets entangled with and obscured by these obstacles of sin and death and the devil present
themselves.
Right?
But they're not the real issue.
Right, they're not the real issue.
They're not what salvation is really about.
They're not what human life is really about.
They're these foreign invaders.
We get rid of them.
We get healthy.
We get rid of the infection.
Now we're ready to get back to business.
Now we're ready to get to work.
That's also my final comments.
So you can go ahead and close this out.
Oh, wow. Okay.
To give you the last words, so take all the shabby.
Hey, well, I mean usually I get the first words,
and then you take the last words.
But so I, you know, as I've been working through this,
since we were briefing on it, and of course,
I'm having this conversation here on the air,
I've been trying to think about the best way to encapsulate
this to some extent so that people can have a good clear takeaway.
But
but also something that they can communicate to other people as well.
And what I came up with here, right, actually just a few minutes ago, as you were speaking
here at the end, is I think that most conversations about salvation, as you said, a lot of sermons
you're going to hear in other churches, is about what you're saved from.
It's about what you're saved from.
And that's not wrong.
Okay, we're definitely saved from a number of things short list demons sin and death.
That's what we're saved from.
And you know, it's important to go through like what St. Paul calls the elementary doctrines
of Christ.
We need that stuff.
This is this is catacism and we need to be reminded of it.
We need to be kind of refocused on it read centered on it.
It's absolutely critical.
right? But it's, but it's only one part of the picture that what you're saved from.
There's also what you're saved for. What you're saved for, right? And I think this is the
big problem with this whole, you know, are you going to heaven or hell when you die?
Like I'm saved from hell so I can go to heaven. Well, what is heaven? Well, it's not hell.
It's great. In fact, or I guess if you're Alexander Kalamero's there, they're the same thing.
just you know some people do it differently.
But no there's a saved.
four, right? So in Ephesians chapter two, St. Paul says, this is starting with verse
eight, for by grace, you have been saved through faith or through faithfulness. And this
is not your own doing it is the gift of God, not a result of works so that no one may
boast. And as we've talked about before on the show, you know, faithfulness is that through
which we are saved. And the path of faithfulness, you know, this is not your own doing God, you
You didn't come up with it.
God gave you this path of faithfulness, right?
And when he says it's not a result of work so that no one may boast, you know, you can
certainly read that in the way that every Protestant naturally would, which is like, no,
you can't earn your way to heaven.
Okay, yes, we agree with that.
But also speaking to Ephesians, former pagans, it's not the result of like works, you know,
great feats of greatness, like the demigods do.
and the pagan context, you know, that's the means through which you gain the blissfulness
of the gods, right? So it's not that. But then it says this in verse 10, this is the part I want to
focus on. For we are his workmanship created in Christ Jesus for good works which God prepared
beforehand that we should walk in them. This is what we are saved for. This is what we were
created for.
that we should walk in them. So we're saved from demons and in death. Yes, it's okay to save your save from
demination. That's fine, but you're saved for
participation in the energies of God. You're saved for
doing the works of God. You're saved for
doing what Adam and Eve were given at the very beginning.
cultivate this world, put this world
order, shape this world and fill it with life, fill it with all kinds of life. This is what we're
made for, right? And so the life of repentance then is not only the stuff you're saved from,
getting rid of the stuff you saved from, although yeah, you got to do that. You got to turn
turn your back on Demonson and Death. You gotta do that. But it's also what you say
for.
And so we're not waiting into the life of the age to come to start doing the works of God.
We're supposed to be doing them now.
And so much I think of the existential experience that people have with trying to repent.
It's just kind of a lengthy exercise of trying to say stop it to themselves.
Stop it.
Stop sinning.
which okay, you know, maybe in the moment.
of sin, you need to at least hear that voice, cut it out, you know, stop it. But the way to
grow out of the desire for sin is to practice the virtues, it's to practice the good works of God.
Often when we focus simply on trying to stop sin, actually that can become very, very self-absorbed.
Look at me, look at all the bad things I-
do. I need to stop it. And then, you know, we can kind of wallow and guilt. And guilt
does not repentance, folks. And of course, then usually at some point comes despair and
despair least all kinds of bad stuff. But if we do the works of faithfulness that God has
given us to do. If we walk in them as St. Paul says, these good works
God prepared for forehand for us that we are created in Christ Jesus for good works.
Then we become more like Christ.
Then our wills are aligned with the will of God and they no longer are leaning in the
direction of sin.
Instead they're trained in the direction of Christ, they're trained in the direction of
beauty, they're trained in the direction of goodness, love, long suffering, faithfulness,
generosity, worship all of these.
So how do you repent?
I mean, do the stuff you're pre-skeleton keeps telling you to do.
That's the way.
Christ says, if you love me, you keep my commandments.
That pairing of love and keeping the commandments of God is everywhere in the Bible.
Everywhere, over and over and over and over again.
And that's how we become like Christ.
That's what we are saved for.
four or say four good works were saved.
to become equal to the angels.
That's not just a status, it's not just a title of sons of God.
It's also work to do.
It's also taking care of this world,
and that includes other people above all else, really.
So, yeah, it's not just what we're saved from,
it's what we're saved for.
And indeed, the more that we focus on what we're saved for,
the more that what we're saved from withers and dies
and has
no power over you. So especially as we're finishing up Great Land here and we're about to head
into Holy Week in Paska. I hope that these these great gems from the Holy Scriptures
will be a source of encouragement and joy, frankly, for everyone out there. So well,
that's our show for tonight. Thank you for listening, everybody. If you didn't happen
to his life. Unlike those two men named John from Missouri, we
Please select to hear from you.
You can email us, Lordofspirits at AncientFate.com.
You can message us on our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lordofspirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or you need help finding a parish,
go to Orthodoxintro.org and you'll get some good responses.
And join us for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at
6 p.m. Eastern 3 p.m. Pacific.
You look like a perfect fit for a girl in need of a tourniquet.
if you're on Facebook.
you can follow our page, you can join our big old discussion group and leave ratings and reviews
wherever you get your podcasts and please share this show with one of your friends.
And finally be sure to go to www.inxfaith.com.stokesupport to help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasts stay on the air because I can tell you know what it's like, the long farewell of the
hunker strike. Thank you. Good night and may God bless you always.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter five, verses 11 through 12.